AUTHOR’S NOTE, 1990

The tale here set forth of Finn and Hildeburh grew out of a small portion of the Old English heroic poem Beowulf. After Beowulf’s victory over the monster Grendel, the hero and his brave companions gather together in Heorot, the famous hall of Danish king Hrothgar, to celebrate. In that portion of the poem, often called “The Finnsburg Episode of Beowulf” (lines 1064–1124), Hrothgar’s poet sings a song about the famous battle of Finn and Hnaef. The tale is retold in brief by the Beowulf poet—a story within a story, as it were. At the time that Beowulf was composed, that tale of Finn and Hildeburh was probably well-known, and so the Beowulf poet needed only to give a brief summary of the events. Now, however, many centuries later, the full story of these events is long lost. All we know of the tragic tale of Finn is what we read in that small episode of Beowulf, and in a cryptic fragment of another poem which was discovered, transcribed by the scholar George Hickes, and then lost, but which seems to relate closely to the events told by the Beowulf poet.

Here then is given, as recreated in the imagination of the author, a fuller tale of Finn and Hildeburh, and of the events leading up to the fight at Finnsburg. No knowledge of Beowulf is necessary, but those who are familiar with that great poem may enjoy these speculations. In order to give a more realistic, historical flavor to the tale, I have placed the events during a particular period of history, namely the early seventh century. This proved to be a rather troublesome business, for it raised many difficult questions. Are the events of the Finn Episode based on a real battle? Did these people really exist in history? If so, when? We don’t know the answers to these questions. Thus in some sense this time frame is rather arbitrary. Historians, Old English scholars, and archaeologists have argued over the dating of the Beowulf poem for years. Some have dated the poem’s composition as early as 500, and others as late as 1000. The closest one can come to a general consensus would be in the mid-800s, but that is really more of a compromise than a consensus. The tale of Finn, if already well-known by the time Beowulf was composed, must have taken place long before. If Beowulf was composed in 500, then the tale of Finn obviously could not have taken place after 600! My dating of the tale is as much for the sake of convenience as anything; there were some things about that period, such as the founding of Lindisfarne, that I wanted to include in my tale. But there are a few other good reasons for setting my story during that time. It has been suggested that the Hengest of this tale is one and the same as the Hengest who in the late sixth century finally defeated the remnant forces of the Britons under the famed British warleader, King Arthur. But once again, knowledge of these dates and events is not at all necessary to the enjoyment of the tale set forth here, which was written to stand on its own.

I would give my deepest thanks to Professor Robert Farrell of Cornell University. His expertise in medieval archaeology and Old English language and literature was invaluable to me. In addition to much enthusiastic encouragement, he also provided the critical eye that is so necessary to a novel like this. Considerable thanks are also due to Jan Dennis of Crossway Books for his encouragement and work with me on this project. There is no doubt that without the two of them, this would not have been written.

Matthew T. Dickerson

August 1990

AUTHOR’S NOTE, 2021

It is interesting to go back to a novel I wrote more than three decades ago. I have changed as a writer over that time. Over the course of more than a dozen books written and published between then and now, I like to think I have improved in my craft. So it is very tempting to revise my earlier work, polishing and refining the prose of my younger self. Yet I have resisted that temptation. Any attempt at improving the prose, no matter how restrained I sought to be, would undoubtably also make the new version more representative of my current style. Which is to say, it would become a different book even if it remained the same “story”. So despite the strong temptation, the only edits I have made have been to correct one typo that has bothered me since the book was published. (Any other changes or typos likely arose from the process of converting the text to digital form from the scan of a printed version.)

For the truth is, I think the story still holds beauty for me, however many flaws I find in my telling of it. When I wrote it, it held many surprises for me. And I’ve heard from numerous readers who have told me the same thing.

I also grew to care about the characters as I got to know them better—both the literary figures (Folcwalda, Finn, Hildeburh, and Finnlaf) and also those that emerged from my own author’s imagination (especially Willimond, Ulestan, Kristinge, and Daelga). Indeed, I enjoyed getting to know these characters so much, and spending time immersed in the world in which they lived, that I wanted to tell more of their stories, and to get to know them better. I eventually did in the sequel novel The Rood and the Torc: the Song of Kristinge, Son of Finn (Wings Press, 2014).

I hope readers are still able to find delight in these two stories.

Matthew T. Dickerson

March 2021

I

Of Finn, Son of Folcwalda

Atop a small tower of stone overlooking the bay, as still and unmovable as the rock beneath him, stood Finn, the prince of Friesland. His unfaltering gaze scanned the far horizon for a sail upon the waters. Out across Hwitstanwic and beyond his eyes roamed, to the great North Sea from whence would come his heart’s desire. He wore a red cloak of fine woven cloth, fastened at the waist with bright blue silk and decorated at the shoulders in green. Healfwyrhta, his mighty battle sword, hung from a loose strap over his back. An old treasure it was, proven times without count. In his left hand he held his great ash staff. And on a chain about the prince’s neck was a polished ivory battle horn, new-made and not yet winded; richly decorated in silver by Deomaer the jeweler, it was a treasure worthy of a king.

Long had Finn waited for this day, and with no small labor had he prepared. This was his day. Many months of hope and longing would finally come to an end. It was Summer’s Day, the day of the long sun. This was the day when Finn the strong, Folcwalda’s son, wielder of Healfwyrhta, was to wed Hildeburh the fair, the jewel of the Danes, Hnaef-sister and Hoc-daughter, whose beauty was said to surpass even that of the empresses of the Fair Folk. It was for Hildeburh that Finn now waited, standing motionless upon his tower as he had for three long days. When she arrived, there would be a celebration and feast whose equal Hwitstan would not again see for many generations of men.

Before the sun had climbed halfway into the sky, the men and women of Hwitstan began to gather upon the hill overlooking Hwitstanwic to await the arrival of the Danes. Their work had been done; the preparations were complete. Never in their days had they seen such an abundance of fare as now awaited them in the village, and they were eager for it. More than a dozen wild boar had been killed and were already roasting over the fresh-dug fire pits back in the village. There would be pork for all—thanes, earls and commoners alike. Fish, too, they had in abundance; the weirs of Laguhunta and Lopystre had provided richly that spring. And of mead and beer, there was enough to quench the thirst of the entire village for a month and a day!

Deomaer, the jeweler and moneyer of King Folcwalda, stood among those waiting. As his eyes searched the horizon for a sight of the Danish ships, his thoughts drifted back, and he remembered the day when he had first heard of Finn’s betrothal to the Danish princess. He had only recently returned to Hwitstan from the Jutish and Saxon lands on the Isle of the Britons. The last vestiges of winter were still upon Friesland …

•

Deomaer braced himself against the bitter chill in the air as he stepped out of his hut. The spring equinox was one week past, but the early morning still held the bite of winter. Ahead of him, a small circle of huts was beginning to emerge out of the slowly dissipating fog. There was yet no sign of life. He glanced up briefly and saw the first grey of dawn appearing in a clear sky, then turned his eyes downward, pulled his wool cloak tightly about him to protect his ears, and turned to head up the hill.

His hut was on the northern side of Hwitstan—the seaward side—so he had no need of crossing through the village to get to the sea. Like most of the huts in the village, his was a long, rectangular hole, three feet deep, with turf walls which rose a foot above ground and a sloping roof of timbers and skins. A heavy ox hide covered the doorway, which faced southward—away from the prevailing winter winds and into the village. Deomaer’s hut was larger than some. It had two rooms. The front one was small and simple, containing only a short mat where Deomaer slept and a low table with two chairs. The back room was larger and contained the tools and devices of his trade. Deomaer was a jeweler, and soon, though he knew it not at the time, he was to be a moneyer as well.

Deomaer could feel the stiff breeze on his cheeks and ears as he walked around the back of his hut and started up the hill which separated village from sea. He trudged up it, keeping his head lowered to avoid the worst of the wind. A startled rabbit darted ahead a few yards, and then veered off to the right where it dove under a clump of grass. A flock of blackbirds rose from a bush to his left and flew as a group over the village and then down toward the pond. He lifted his head for a moment to watch them and then lowered it again. By the time he reached the summit there was a warm red glow filling the eastern horizon.

Standing atop the hill, surrounded by the first rays of the morning sun, stood a solitary silhouette. Deomaer recognized him at once; his size and stature were unmistakable. It was Finn, his prince.

Finn was a tall man, nearly a head taller than Deomaer; taller indeed than any in the village save only his father, King Folcwalda. He stood there still and silent, his left hand holding a sturdy ash staff and his right hanging casually at his side. His dark hair fell loosely to his shoulders, where it partially covered a long scar running across his collarbone from the base of his neck to his shoulder. From head to foot, every inch of Finn was a warrior and prince. Even through his heavy winter cloak, Deomaer could see Finn’s finely tuned shoulders and the strength in his powerful arms. His hands and forearms were like tough leather shields—shields which had held steadfast through battle after battle and bore proudly’ the marks from all. And his legs were as sturdy as a young ash. A heavy broadsword, too long to hang at his side, was slung over the prince’s back. And, though he couldn’t see them then, Deomaer knew the prince’s face as well, especially his dark green eyes. They were deep-set under a stern brow and seemed able to see right through whatever they were fixed upon. More than once Deomaer had felt that penetrating glance upon himself. It was a glance at once both fierce and compassionate. Finn was a prince whom one would be proud to serve. He was a prince for whom one would die.

As the jeweler stepped to the crest of the hill behind Finn, his eyes moved from the back of his prince to the magnificent view spread before him. The sparkling North Sea stretched out in three directions as far as the eye could see. He involuntarily held his breath for a moment and then let out a long sigh. He had seen the great sea a thousand times before, but it still filled him with awe.

The lone figure tensed at the sudden sound of Deomaer’s sigh. His jaw jutted out slightly, and the grip on his staff tightened. Deomaer froze as he saw the muscles bunching up on the neck and shoulder of the prince. Finn’s battle-hardened warrior’s instincts had been aroused. In a moment of irrational fear Deomaer half-expected Finn’s staff to come swinging around into his skull, or to see the sword loosed from off his prince’s shoulders. But those things did not happen. Instead, the prince just as quickly relaxed his stance and turned to face the one who was intruding on his solitude.

“My lord,” Deomaer said, kneeling before Finn. He knelt not only because Finn was his prince, which was reason enough, but because he was in awe of him. Such authority did he command that had Finn been a slave and not a prince, Deomaer might still have found himself kneeling before him.

“Rise and stand beside me, Deomaer, son of Dunlaf,” Finn said. His voice was full and rich and laden with hidden power. But this morning it held the tone of invitation rather than of command. Deomaer rose. His awe of Finn increased his pride at the words his prince had spoken to him. “Stand beside me,” he had said.

“Look across the sea, Dé,” Finn began. Again Deomaer tingled with pride—Finn had addressed him with his familiar name. “To the north and west …” the prince began. Then he paused and gestured toward the sea with a broad sweep of his free arm. From the way the prince was casually addressing him, Deomaer might have thought his prince had been expecting him. Yet, he had seen a brief moment of surprise registered in Finn’s muscles a few seconds earlier when he had walked up behind him and sighed.

“To the north and west of us, across the Swan Road, lies the land of the Britons where the Angles and Saxons now rule. To the north and east,” he continued, adjusting his grip on his staff and pointing just north of the rising sun, “lies the land of the Danes. And south of us,” he finished, turning around and looking out over Hwitstan, “is the Merovingian kingdom—the land of the Franks. And beyond the Frankish kingdoms lie all of the great kingdoms of the continent. Our land stands at the center of these like a young sapling in the midst of a great oak forest.”

Deomaer nodded mutely. He was trying his best to catch the import of the words spoken to him by his prince. Was Finn simply verbalizing his thoughts to the first person who happened by? Or had he wanted to speak to Deomaer in particular? Probably the former, Deomaer guessed. Nonetheless, Finn was speaking to him alone; he had used the word “our”; he had spoken of “our land”—the land of Finn and Deomaer. “Stand beside me,” he had said. He had said that to Deomaer! Deomaer was standing beside his prince talking with him—or at least listening to him. The Jutish princes and thanes in Cantbury, or anywhere in Cantwara, never spoke with the commoners.

Finn glanced at Deomaer for a moment to ensure that he was listening and then continued. As he did, his voice began to grow slightly louder and took on a tone of urgency, or if not of urgency, then at least of importance. “The Frisian people have always been poor—our clan not the least among them. We are few in number and have no great power. Had not the Franks been so busy fighting amongst themselves, we would certainly have come under their dominion in your father’s father’s days. And now, reunited under the kinslayer Chlotar the younger, we have the greater reason to fear them. United by such treachery, they are all the more dangerous.”

“We have spears …” Deomaer began to object, but Finn silenced him with a quick gesture.

“Spears will do nothing for us … or at least not yet. We stand now at a crossroads, Deomaer. The young sapling must grow or it will surely die. It cannot live in the shadows of the great trees forever. As I have said, we have great kingdoms on every side of us. This is a threat, yes; yet, we must remember that it is our one great advantage as well.”

Deomaer looked puzzled.

“The wealth that we have, little though it may be now, has been gained from trade,” the prince continued in answer to Deomaer’s unasked question. “The best trade routes in northern Europe pass our shores, and the amount of trade continues to increase with each season. As the kingdoms around us grow, so does the trade.”

“Folcwalda has used this trade to great advantage,” Deomaer responded. “Have we not more wealth than ever before?”

“Yes,” Finn answered proudly. “He is a good king.” Between Folcwalda and his son Finn, there was none of the rivalry that so often separated a king from his princes. “He has established the beginnings of our wealth and the foundations of our kingdom. He is the first true king of our people. Never before have the Frisians been united in such as way as they are now.”

He paused for a moment as if to honor his father, and then continued, “Nonetheless there is still much to be done.” His voice gathered force. “Yes, there is much left to be done. We must act now. We must seize the opportunity given us.” As he said the word “seize” his right hand swung around and gripped his staff, and he lifted it into the air. A sudden energy seemed to possess the prince. He straightened to his full stature and held his staff as if it were a weapon—the staff of power of Briton’s Druid. For a moment he was a giant to Deomaer, like the great Eormenric returned from the dead. “Friesland is destined to rise and become a great kingdom …” He swung the staff high around his head. “… or to be crushed by the growing powers around it.” The staff came crashing into the ground.

A shiver passed through Deomaer’s spine, and he unconsciously pulled his cloak more tightly about his shoulder. Finn stood still for a moment, staring at the ground where his staff had put a small dent in the hard earth. Then he relaxed his stance, and the energy and passion which had possessed him slowly subsided to remain hidden in reserve, simmering below the surface. He began speaking once more, this time almost to himself. “We may yet become that great nation—like the Scyldings in the days of Beow—wielding such strength that others will bow down and pay tribute to us. But that day has not yet come; we have not the might to stand on our own against those who surround us. And so we must rely on trade and hope to survive. Trade has given us the wealth we have, and trade will make us stronger still. We must both protect and increase our trade. We must nurture what we have. We cannot survive great wars such as those which brought low the Britons and Geats, and even the mighty Rome. Yet neither may we afford to lose this land.”

Deomaer nodded in agreement. He was still staring at Finn’s staff, expecting at any moment for it to burst into flames under some spell from its wielder.

“In times past we have had little trouble. That is true,” Finn said. “Weak though we were, and few in number, yet there were none who came against us in force. For apart from the trade which passes through our shores, our land seems barren and of little value. But do not be fooled! There are many now who envy our land and shores, for by them we control the trade routes. Hwitstan only exists because of Hwitstanwic. Without Hwitstanwic …” Finn continued, gesturing once again toward the coastlands and the sheltered beaches in front of them, “we have nothing. Because we rely on our trade, we must be able to defend our beaches and landings. I speak not merely for Hwitstan, but for all of the Frisian people—for all of Friesland. Our trade and our land are in peril.”

“My lord,” Deomaer objected, breaking out of his trance, “you know that your people will stand beside you in war.”

Finn smiled. “I know you would. Who has ever had a more loyal hearthwerod? I do not doubt the valor of my people. But we are few, and war is ugly. When I speak of enemies, I speak not only of the Franks. Though they are the closest and strongest of the surrounding kingdoms, Chlotar their king is not the only threat to our people. You have seen Cantbury in Cantwara, the land of the Jutes. You know how rich and powerful they are. And Cantbury is but one of many Jutish cities, and the Jutes are but one of many tribes and kingdoms. They are as quick to unite as they are to fight amongst themselves. You know of Ethelfrith; his burial was a tribute to his greatness. At time of need, all of the Angles from Deira to Bernicia were united under his kingship to drive the last of the Britons out of their land. And to the south of them, the Saxons have been united by Ethelbert. Where will they go—the Angles, the Saxons, and the Jutes—when they have filled the land of the Britons? They will seek new land. It is their way. Surely you have not forgotten that Friesland itself was not always the land of the Frisians. Ten and five generations have our people dwelt on these shores, and yet others there were who were driven out before us. And if we are not careful, others there will be who will follow after.”

Deomaer had forgotten. It was before the days even of his forefathers’ forefathers when his people had settled the land. Yet who, he wondered, had been driven out before them?

“As I have said,” Finn continued, “we are a small kingdom in the midst of many mightier ones. So what shall we do? We must be able to defend ourselves, and yet war must be a last resort. Our hope is in trade.” Then, almost as if it were an afterthought, Finn added, “And were we the most powerful kingdom on either side of the seas, war would still remain but a last hope when all else had failed. War is always tragic no matter who the victor is.”

War is tragic? Deomaer thought to himself. Is not war glorious? Or so we have bee told since the kings of old. The chieftains were chieftains because they led their people in battle! What of Finn? Was he so different from the kings and chieftains of the north? Yet Deomaer himself was no warrior. What did he know of the clash of spears? “And if we must fight?” he said out loud. “If all else does fail?” It seemed to Deomaer that his prince was leading somewhere; that there was a riddle with the answer about to be revealed. What had Finn said? That they were not strong enough alone to survive a war against their neighbors, but that ‘they must still defend their shores at need if they were to protect their trade. Then the question was how.

“What better way to prevent war,” Finn answered, “or if war comes, what better way to win than to have a strong ally?”

Was this the answer to the riddle? Was Finn seeking allies? Among whom? Certainly not the Franks. Chlotar was treacherous. He could never be trusted, he who slew his own king. The Saxons? Possibly. They were kindred peoples. The Jutes as well. They would certainly be more faithful allies than the Franks. But they were far across the sea. Perhaps too far. Was Finn speaking of Rome? The emperor was even further away than the Saxon kings and had little contact with Friesland. Though once mighty, the Empire was now weak and unsteady, overrun and conquered every generation. Agiluf’s rule had lasted only twenty-five years. A treaty with the South would bring no real benefit to Finn.

“Of what ally are you speaking, my lord?” Deomaer finally asked.

Finn answered his question with one of his own—something which in years to come Deomaer would realize was a favorite habit of his. “What ally is more sure than one which is bound by blood?”

“None, my lord,” Deomaer answered, bowing his head. “But where do we find such an ally?”

“Where indeed, my friend Dé? Where indeed!” A broad smile slowly spread across the prince’s face. “You know of the Danes.”

It was a comment, not a question. Certainly Deomaer knew of the Danes. They were powerful, fierce, aggressive warriors. He had seen them sail on more than one occasion during his time in Cantwara. Even the proud Saxons sung of the Danes with fear and respect:

Shields make you ready,
Round, hard, and fast,

When ships of Spear-Danes sail to the bay!
Swords boldly swing

Swiftly and strong
For gold and our treasure

Must trade for our lives.

For good reason the name of the Spear-Danes was well known on every side of the great North Sea. Yes, Deomaer knew of them. He nodded his answer, and Finn continued.

“Ten weeks from now a Danish ship will arrive in this port. That ship will be carrying Hildeburh, sister of Hnaef, son of Hoc, the king of the Danes.”

Was this what Finn was getting to? Did he want the Danes to come to Friesland? Few kings there were who desired to see Danish ships on their shores. “What of Hildeburh, my lord?” Deomaer asked.

“She is to be my wife,” the prince replied. He could no longer contain his grin. It grew as broad as his face.

Deomaer remained silent for a moment as he considered this news. Then an answering smile spread across his face as well. A treaty with the Danes would gain instant respect for the Frisians, if not fear of them. There were few if any who would dare attack the Danes—or, he hoped, their allies. And even more importantly, the Frisians would be safe from the Spear-Danes themselves. What king would attack his own blood, particularly a sister! Finn was gaining the best treaty he possibly could with the Danes: the treaty of marriage.

Deomaer stared at his prince in admiration, seeking for appropriate words. The only thing he could think of was to drop to his knee again. This he did. “My lord,” he said, turning his eyes downward. Like Folcwalda his father, Finn would make a good king someday. Deomaer was glad to serve him. More than that, he was honored.

Finn just laughed—a deep, full laugh—and then pulled Deomaer roughly to his feet. “The work is just beginning, Deomaer, son of Dunlaf, master jeweler of Hwitstan.” His free hand came to rest lightly on Deomaer’s shoulder. “It is time to put you to the test and see if my father sent you to apprentice in Cantbury for nothing. Are your hands now as skilled as the famous jewelers of Cantbury? What have you learned in your five years across the Swan Road? Will you make my land as famous as Cantbury of Cantwara?”

“We shall see, my lord.” Deomaer bowed. “I am at your service.”

“Yes, we shall see,” Finn said. “For the next three months your new forges shall be blazing without ceasing. There will be a never-ending stream of gold and silver passing through your doors. I want rings for my thanes, wound gold for our necks, silver handles for our blades, and coins for our harbors—yes, a coin in honor of Folcwalda! And most importantly, Dé, the prize of your work, the heart of your labor, the treasure of my kingdom beside which all other treasures shall pale—I want jewels and necklaces for my wife which shall surpass all jewelry worn by any queen of the Angles, Saxons, Danes, Scyldings, Geats or any people anywhere. My queen is to be the crown of my head and the chief treasure of the Frisians. As she will be my crown, so too shall she have a crown beyond value.”

There was a sparkle in Finn’s eyes as he spoke of Hildeburh, and Deomaer wondered for the first time if there was more to the marriage than a convenient treaty between two kings. Why had Folcwalda—or was it Finn himself—chosen Hildeburh of the Danes? Deomaer wondered how much more was involved than simply the renown of the Danish spears. Folcwalda, it was said, thought and planned far beyond what even the most astute of his thanes could comprehend. And now Finn seemed to possess that trait as well. A treaty with the Spear-Danes was certainly good news.

But to the young jeweler all those thoughts paled beside the fact that Finn had put his hand on his shoulder and called him by his familiar name a second time.

“Return now to your home, Dé, and prepare for your work,” Finn said, breaking into Deomaer’s thoughts. “Keep this secret between us for just a short time. Very soon the whole village will know the joyous news, and then we will all celebrate together—a brief celebration now and a greater one soon!”

The prince had confided in him. “Keep this secret between us.” He had used the word “us.” With awe and admiration for Finn, and no little pride at having been held in his confidence, Deomaer turned and walked back down toward the village. He considered stopping at the first hut he passed and waking the inhabitants to announce that Finn had spoken to him in private. No, the first dwelling belonged to Folcwalda. Better not to awaken him. Instead, Deomaer returned to his own hut where he held back what would have been a very loud shout. He would do all he could to make Finn’s name famous across the seas. Folcwalda was a good king. One day Finn would be too. Deomaer was determined to be his loyal follower.

II

The Gathering of the Hearthwerod

The same day that Finn had announced his betrothal to Hildeburh had also seen the beginning of the building of a great hall in Hwitstan. Though this was but a few months earlier, Hwitstan had been a much smaller village then, smaller than many in Friesland. When Deomaer had returned from Cantwara, Hwitstan had contained only twenty or so huts scattered around a small clearing. There had been a few livestock and rabbit pens on the west side of the village, and the small stream which flowed through Hwitstan had been dammed a few hundred paces before it tumbled down the hill and into the river after which the village took its name, there forming a little pond.

Yet though village and clan were small, it had gained much power in Friesland. This was due entirely to the strength and wisdom of its chieftain, Folcwalda. He had succeeded in uniting nearly all of Friesland into a single kingdom. Only a few Frisian clans still preferred their independence and resisted taking a High King.

But Folcwalda needed to be able to gather his thanes, earls and retainers before he could fully establish a high kingship in Friesland. Those who had pledged themselves to him, and their warbands with them, needed to be in one place with their king and war leader. And before Folcwalda and Finn could gather their warbands, they required a hall large enough to house them. They needed a hearth around which the people could gather with their treasure-giver. So they had begun the building of Hwitstanburg, as the great hall would be named. And much there was which had needed to be done. Some had begun at once cutting the timbers for the posts and roof, while others dug the fire pit at the center of the hall, and others worked at digging the holes for the wall’s foundation. The timbers, once cut, had to be dragged into the village over rough, hard ground. Great flat stones, some as large as shields, were needed not only for the hearth, but also to place in the ground beneath the posts to prevent them from rot ting or sinking. Those too had to be found and hauled in from the surrounding countryside. This was no small task. Yet despite the difficulties, the work had proceeded at a quick pace, and after only a few days the hall’s outline and form had already begun to become visible. In a few weeks the walls had reached higher than Folcwalda’s head. And then the smith had bound the timbers in place with iron, and the roof‍—‌the most difficult task of all‍—‌had finally been raised. When all that was done, the women did the wattle-work, weaving slender poplar branches in and out of the vertical stakes. The older children had finished the process by filling the gaps with a mud-and-grass daub which, when dried, left a hard, brick-like plaster.

Now, three months after it had been begun, the great hall was finally finished. And with it, atop the nearby hill, stood the new tower Finnweard which overlooked both village and bay alike: Hwitstan and Hwitstanwic.

When all was done, the villagers, many of whom had never traveled more than a day’s walk outside Hwitstan, were in awe of the hall’s size. It was over fifty paces long‍—‌not children’s paces but the paces of a king! Even Deomaer, who had seen the great halls at Cantbury and Oxfordshire, was impressed. The village seemed suddenly more noble.

Nor was the hall the only addition to Hwitstan, for as the hall had grown, so had the village. Surrounding Hwitstanburg in every direction the eye looked, changes had taken place so quickly that few besides Folcwalda and Finn had been able to note or remember them all. The village had grown rapidly as men from the surrounding villages‍—‌Ezinge, Aalsum, Beowic, Heorotburg, and even as far as Dronrip, Wieuwerd and Wijnaldum‍—‌arrived in Hwitstan. New huts had appeared and were still appearing almost daily on the outskirts of the village.

Hwitstan was slowly becoming the center of a new kingdom.

And to Hwitstanburg, newly built, the warbands of Folcwalda and Finn had finally been gathered. Thanes brave and strong, hardy in battle and wise in counsel, came to serve the king whom they had proclaimed over Friesland and to receive treasure from his hand. And treasure they received from the first day they gathered around his hearth. Folcwalda’s hearthwerod they were. Of their mighty deeds, tales would be told and lays sung.

•

Summer’s Day was a day of celebration among the Frisians and Danes alike‍—‌the longest day of the year, the day that the life-giving sun was at the peak of her power. The celebration marked the time of warmth and growth, when animals could graze long and grow fat preparing for the hard winter months ahead, or for the table upon which they would appear. It marked the time when the hours of daylight came in abundance giving ample opportunity to labor and provide, to rebuild and remake, and to prepare for the darker, colder season. Summer’s Day was a day of life. And for the war-tribes it was a time for battle and conquest, for raids and victories and spoils.

It was only fitting that the wedding of Finn, son of Folcwalda, and Hildeburh of the Danes should be on Summer’s Day. It was a new beginning, not for Finn and Hildeburh only, but for all of Friesland.

And for Finn it was a day of proving as well, a day whose importance could not be overlooked. For though Folcwalda had nearly established a high kingship for himself, it would not necessarily be passed to Finn. A strong prince would receive the throne from his father; a weak prince would founder if there were strong chieftains to oppose him. If Finn could indeed marry, as he had promised to his people, the daughter of a powerful Danish king, none would dare oppose him; his claim to his father’s throne would be established. If there were no queen, if the Danes did not sail to Friesland, then he would likely fall. Further, the high kingship would be dissolved.

And the Danes were already late. They were to have come three days before the celebration, but no sail had yet been seen and no word had been heard. Followers of the prince as well as those who jealously eyed the throne wondered at the promises of Finn.

The day of celebration had dawned sunny and warm. The last of the spring rains had finally blown over, and clear blue skies prevailed. Finn’s tower had been completed only days before, and Finn had awakened long before dawn each of the past three days to take his stand atop it. For three mornings he had watched the dawn rise over the eastern hills and had waited alone for the first sign of the incoming ships. As Summer’s Day progressed, more and more people ascended the hill and waited with him, standing in groups at the bottom of the tower while Finn silently kept his vigil above them. While the older villagers stood quietly waiting, eager for the coming celebration and curious about the wonderful Danes of whom they had heard much, the children of Hwitstan, patient and solemn at first, were soon playing down by the water’s edge. The older brothers and sisters busied themselves searching for pieces of amber which had washed ashore during the recent storms, while the younger ran and played in the sand. An occasional shout of joy would erupt, and one or another child would come rushing up the hill carrying a smooth piece of sea polished amber which they would present with pride to their parents.

Folcwalda, meanwhile, sat in council with his thanes. Soon after the completion of Hwitstanburg, they had joined him beneath its roof. And from that day forth they were blessed by their treasure-giver. Rings crafted by Deomaer, gold and silver alike, and battle-hardy weapons as well, that generous king did give in abundance to his thanes. And land too he gave to those who served him. Folcwalda’s earls did not suffer any lack when they served their king within his hall. So as Prince Finn stood upon the tower waiting, Folcwalda’s hearthwerod was gathered beneath the roof of Hwitstanburg. The benches had been set in place, and a fire was lit upon the great hearth.

In all of Hwitstan only the king’s chefs and their apprentices labored still in preparation. They stood beside the roasting pits, turning the pigs on their spits and watching to see that they cooked evenly. Though some perhaps were jealous of those who sat at ease enjoying the day, they nonetheless approached their task with great care‍—‌and rightly so! A tale still circulated among them of a certain Jutish chef who, by neglect, had burned a cow while roasting it and had then served the vastly overcooked meat to the king. Livestock being as precious as it was, the king was greatly displeased. He sentenced the chef to the task of replacing the cow, a task at which the chef failed. The chef’s death at the hands of that king was not at all pleasant. Folcwalda, though he was not wont to kill one of his servants, nonetheless encouraged the proliferation of that story among his cooks. He had Daelga, his poet, sing it to them at least once a year. Since Daelga had first told that tale among them, Folcwalda had not once been fed burned meat.

Mid-morning of Summer’s Day came and passed, and so did midday. Finn kept his vigil, and Folcwalda remained in council with his thanes. The rest of the village watched and waited impatiently. They looked ever and again at Finn, hoping he would notice their impatience and begin the celebration. But the prince’s eyes never dropped below the horizon. He stood in his familiar pose, one hand holding his staff, the other at his side, and his great sword draped across his back. His stance never faltered, nor did his watchfulness ever waver. There was no trace of doubt on his face.

Elsewhere upon the hill and down in the village, restless ness and impatience abounded. After a while even the older and more patient children tired of waiting and returned to the village to play games in the clearing near the great hall. Some of the men began to disperse back to their homes or farms. “In past years,” Deomaer heard someone grumble, “the celebration would have started by now.” The excitement which had been building until midday began to disappear. Many began to suspect that the Danes would not arrive that day. A few even hoped they would never arrive and that the marriage would not take place. Most, however, waited and hoped and trusted in the words of their king and prince.

Deomaer the jeweler was among those who believed in his prince and waited. And as he waited, his thoughts once more retraced the past few weeks.

•

The task he had been given had awed him at first. He was to mint the first Frisian coin‍—‌a coin in honor of Folcwalda. What design could he make for a coin to honor a king? He knew not. Nor was he sure of his ability to craft for Hildeburh, Finn’s future queen, gifts of the beauty and splendor which Finn desired. He also knew the physical difficulty of his work, and that he alone was responsible for the task. In Cantbury the gathering of fuel for the fires had been the job, not of the masters, but of the youngest apprentices. Deomaer had no apprentices. He would need to do it himself, he had thought. But there he had been proven wrong in his fears. Finn had seen that the task was taken care of for him, giving him freedom to concentrate only on his craft.

The same day that work had begun on the hall, gold, silver and wood‍—‌all three in plentiful supply‍—‌had arrived for Deomaer. There were advantages to not being an apprentice any more! Deomaer had been able to begin immediately with the forging of some gold rings. It was a good task for him to start with. It was simple enough work, and would help to bring skill back into his hands which had spent weeks sitting idle. Furthermore, rings would be of immediate use to Folcwalda, who was generous in the giving of them to his thanes. For thanes had already begun arriving in Hwitstan even then, and would come in large numbers at the completion of the hall. When Deomaer’s hands had relearned their trade through simple ring-making, he would begin his first task of real importance: the minting of a Frisian coin.

Yes, Deomaer had reminded himself, he was to be not only a jeweler, but a moneyer‍—‌the moneyer. Finn had not told him of this during their conversation upon the hill. Perhaps it had been Folcwalda’s decision, one which Finn hadn’t even known. Deomaer had felt both honored and afraid when he had been told a few days later by Folcwalda himself that he was to be his moneyer. Moneyer was a position of far greater importance than that of jeweler‍—‌though in Deomaer’s mind one less interesting, for it allowed him less creativity. Jeweling was only a trade; moneying was an office! The coin he would mint would not only be the first Frisian coin, but the only Frisian coin. He would have to guarantee the constancy of the weight of all the coins he minted. Folcwalda’s rune, and perhaps even his own, would be on each coin. As trade passed through Friesland, the coin would be carried throughout the continent and across the sea, perhaps even to his old master who would no doubt recognize the work of his former apprentice.

Deomaer laughed at the thoughts he had had. For a time he had envisioned poets singing in the same breath of Weland the smith and Deomaer the jeweler and moneyer. He laughed again. No, he would not become famous for the minting of a coin.

Once Deomaer had begun his work, gold and silver had come pouring through his doors in a steady stream. And he had known that as fast as it came in, his king had expected it out again in the form of rings. He had worked long, hard hours during those first few weeks. Where the precious metals were coming from, he did not know, nor could he guess, nor had he even time to wonder. There seemed to be a limitless supply. It was arriving faster than he could use it! Five years before, when he had first left the Frisian shores and sailed to Cantbury to be apprenticed to the master jeweler there, his village had been even smaller and poorer than it was when he returned. There was neither gold nor silver in great amounts. Why, he had wondered when he left, did Folcwalda even want a jeweler at all? But as a child of thirteen summers, he was not one to oppose the wishes of his chieftain‍—‌particularly not a chieftain of Folcwalda’s might and stature! Furthermore, the winter before he had been sent away, both of his parents had died of the fever. Maybe Folcwalda had known that the two things Deomaer needed most were a change of scenery and something to keep him busy‍—‌a task to which he could devote himself. But later, when he saw the pounds of gold and silver coming through his door, it became obvious to Deomaer that Folcwalda had been acting on foresight. Folcwalda had known that there would soon be enough gold to warrant a jeweler, and he had planned for it.

Thinking of Folcwalda’s great wisdom and insight, Deomaer had struck upon an idea: a coin that would be worthy of a king. He had been working in the heat of his forge, sweat pouring off his brow, his hands rapidly twisting the gold into elaborate serpentine arm bands, when he had a sudden, clear picture of exactly what he wanted to do. He had at once set aside his gold and tools and quickly grabbed a piece of char-blackened wood. With it, he began to draw the imagined coin on a piece of stone beside his hearth. He rushed to finish the drawing before the ideas faded from his mind. As soon as he had finished his drawing, he knew he had what he wanted. The coin he envisioned would bear the image of the great seabird riding the trade winds. It would symbolize both Folcwalda’s love of the sea and the trade routes which established his kingdom. The great bird, with its piercing, far-seeing eyes, would also serve to remind Friesland and the world of the long-sighted vision of King Folcwalda, who had united all of Friesland into a single kingdom to stand against the Merovingians; who through marriage would gain the Spear Danes as his allies; and who had had the foreknowledge to send a young clanchild, the son of his nephew, to apprentice with the master jewelers across the sea before his own kingdom even had any gold‍—‌in fact, before he even had a kingdom. King Folcwalda who had built the hall at Hwitstan which would stand until the poets sang of it. King Folcwalda, the long-sighted seabird riding the trades.

Deomaer had begun work on the coin at once, first carving out the mould that he would use to stamp the gold and silver, and then measuring the blanks of fixed weight. It took him many tries before he was satisfied with his mould.

III

Of Hildeburh Daughter of Hoc

As it had with the coin, inspiration for Hildeburh’s jewelry had also eventually come to Deomaer, though not without some prompting from Finn. The prince had unexpectedly appeared at the jeweler’s hut late one morning, startling him into dropping his work. The prince had looked tired, Deomaer remembered, but his expression had been eager—as if he thought that by helping Deomaer complete his work sooner he could shorten the days until the arrival of Hildeburh and the Danes. Deomaer still vividly remembered the conversation that had followed. Indeed, he remembered every word that the prince had ever spoken to him, such was his awe of Finn.

“Do I interrupt your work?” Finn had asked, gesturing at the tools in Deomaer’s hand.

Deomaer shook his head no and put them down.

“Then come,” Finn said. “Let us walk some distance and talk.”

Deomaer nodded and followed Finn out the door, leaving the hot gold ring on the stone where it had fallen and bent.

Finn spoke casually to him as they passed southward through the village. “You have seen where we have cleared space for a tower?” At that time Finnweard had not yet been begun.

“The place seems well chosen, my lord. It is not the tallest hill, but it offers the best view of Hwitstanwic and the coastline.”

“Indeed,” Finn replied.

“Your father has much foresight.”

“The tower was of my own planning,” Finn said. It was a simple statement of fact and not a boast. “I have seen many towers along the Saxon and Danish shores, and each time I have thought of this hill.”

“With a lantern on top,” Deomaer said, “it could also act as a guide for ships.” He was thinking of the few Jutish and Saxon burgs he had seen with towers rising from the corners. They somehow seemed better equipped for defense than did Hwitstan.

“Whose ships?” Finn replied, narrowing his eyes a bit and focusing them on Deomaer.

“What?” Deomaer asked, feeling a bit uncomfortable under Finn’s scrutiny and forgetting for a second what he had just said. “Oh … Any ships, I suppose.”

“Yes, any ships, or any person’s ships. And when would a ship need a lantern to find the landing at Hwitstanwic?”

“At night … on dark nights … if they don’t know the coast well.”

“And who would want to land on our beaches at night?”

Enemies! The answer was obvious, so Deomaer left it unsaid. The tower had been built to help them guard Hwitstanwic, not to help others find it. Trading ships coming during the day could find Hwitstan easily and would have no need of such a light. It was Vikings and raiders who would benefit from such a lamp. The same sheltered beaches which made Friesland’s coastal villages ideal trade locations also made them easy prey for quick raids. Hwitstanwic, as the cove, beaches, and islands beside the village of Hwitstan were called, stood at the mouth of a small river which wound its way north from the nearby village of Ezinge. The cove or small bay formed a natural shelter from the rough North Sea. In addition, the Frisian coast offered another natural protection. Long rows of barrier islands lined most of Friesland. Inside this row of narrow, sandy isles the seas remained relatively mild, even in the worst of storms. Ships carrying war bands as well as trade could pass up and down the calmer inner waters with little trouble.

Most trade routes from the continent passed through Friesland and out to the sea along its many rivers. The Hwitstan was among the smallest of these rivers. It carried only a tiny amount of trade coming down from Ezinge and some small Frisian settlements. The Ems and Weser Rivers to the east were larger and longer than the Hwitstan, and the Rhine and Meuse Rivers to the southwest were larger still. These larger rivers carried most of the trade that came from inland by ship. Would not Folcwalda have been wiser to have established his hall at one of these larger rivers? But who was Deomaer to question Folcwalda! For there were, to be sure, advantages to Hwitstanwic. Because of its natural bay, it was among the best landing sites in Friesland. Furthermore, the Hwitstan River was more centrally located than any of the larger rivers.

As they passed through the village, Deomaer listened while Finn explained his plans for two more towers. He planned to build them on the coast, one on each side of Hwitstanwic, far enough away to sight ships well before they reached the bay, but close enough to signal the tower at Hwitstanwic. And as he listened Deomaer began to think about Hildeburh. He had still not begun to craft anything for her though the day had drawn much closer.

“Tell me about Hildeburh,” he had finally mustered the courage to say.

Finn smiled. That smile, too, Deomaer remembered. It was filled with a joy and mirth that shone often from the prince’s face upon his people. To see Finn’s smile was to desire to serve him. “That question has been written on your face for many days,” the prince had answered. “I wondered when it would find utterance.”

How was Finn able to read his thoughts? A wave of embarrassment flooded over him as he thought about that, but he pursued the question anyway. “Can you tell me about her?”

“There is nothing I would enjoy more than speaking of Hildeburh. I think there are few who could tolerate listening to me,” the prince answered, and then was silent for a moment as the two walked on. Finally he closed his eyes and sighed. They had both stopped walking.

“What is Hildeburh like?” Finn had begun softly. “She is tall and graceful, thinner than her mother and sister, but somehow stronger. Her hair is long and blonde. Her smile is like the harbor on a quiet evening—peaceful and calm, both offering and providing comfort. And her anger? Her anger is like the North Sea in the winter months—fierce, wild and uncontrollable, but never out of control itself and always majestic. She has fifteen years now and possesses all the wisdom of a great queen.”

Again Deomaer wondered how Finn knew so much about Hildeburh. Marriages of kings and princes were most often arranged for political reasons. It was not uncommon for the ceremony to begin with the bride and groom having seen each other only once, or perhaps not at all. This was more true of the larger kingdoms around them than it was of Friesland, but even among the Frisians it was very common for one chieftain to give a sister or daughter to another to seal a treaty. Yet Finn had been speaking of Hildeburh as though he had known her all his life—or all hers. Where had the prince gone, and what he had done while Deomaer was away? He had heard many allusions and rumors. Finn had often disappeared, taking with him, as was his wont, fourteen trusted warriors. He would return from places unknown laden with jewels and treasures uncountable, which he would lay as gifts at his father’s feet. From what distant king he won such gifts, Deomaer did not know. Those who did know—Finn’s thanes and companions—were those with whom Deomaer never had opportunity or reason to speak.

“She has never had a great love for the sea as do her kinsmen,” the prince had continued. “She prefers rather the hills and quiet rivers. She loves the evenings more than mornings, fall more than spring, and the moonlight more than the sun. Her eyes themselves are like two great moons. They can grant you peace or trouble your heart.”

“And which do they do for you?” Deomaer had asked.

“Until I am with her, they stir my heart to wakefulness. But when we finally come together, they will bring peace to my soul.”

Then—whether spontaneously or not Deomaer did not know—Finn had begun to sing.

“Flower of heaven,
Hildeburh fair,

Crossing the sea
In summer she came,

Her hair like silver
Softer than fleece,

Her eyes like the moon
On midwinter’s night.

By Finn was she found
Friesland’s new queen,

Hildeburh fair,
Flower of heaven.”

Finn had begun softly, but the song grew as he continued, until Deomaer stood transfixed by the beauty and power of the prince’s voice. Then Finn was silent. There was now no doubt that this was no simple marriage for the sake of gaining a treaty with the Danes.

In the end Deomaer had crafted what Finn wanted—a treasure worthy of the greatest of queens. A brooch he had made, a brooch not of gold but of silver, silver for a woman who loved the moon. It bore upon its surface the image of the rising moon surrounding a great bird. It was no seabird, but a majestic land bird—a bird of the night, an owl. A silver brooch with a great, white, snowy owl like those in the far north; an owl with its large eyes capable of seeing on all but the darkest nights—capable of seeing and hunting. There were arm rings to match the brooch, all silver and all bearing the moon and the owl. And a special coin just for Hildeburh. On the one side it was the same as Folcwalda’s: the seabird riding the trade winds. On the other side: the moon and the owl. The coin he set in an elaborate necklace—a coin with two sides, symbol of the union of Hildeburh with Finn, son of Folcwalda.

But would the union take place? He knew not. Three days they had waited for the Danes. Summer’s Day was now upon them and indeed was quickly passing. Already midday had come and gone; in fact the third hour after midday was past.

IV

Waiting’s End

“Finn!”

A loud voice caught Deomaer’s attention. He turned around to see from whom it had come. Behind him stood a young man, richly dressed in the battle-dress of a Frisian lord. He was a chieftain, or perhaps a chieftain’s son. Deomaer had not seen him before, but if his attire and voice did not deceive, he was no stranger to Friesland. Though no thane of Folcwalda’s, he had Frisian blood within him. In his hand he held a naked blade, glinting in the sun. His shield was across his shoulder, ready at any moment to be taken in hand. Upon his head was a battle helm.

Behind him to the west, at the edge of the trees upon the crest of the hill, was a small warband, perhaps twenty-five men, all mounted. From whence had they come? Deomaer had neither seen nor heard them arrive.

“Finn, I challenge you!” the voice cried out.

Deomaer stepped backward away from the man. Had he heard the stranger correctly? Who was this who so boldly challenged the prince?

Finn made no reply.

“Finn, son of Folcwalda, I challenge you again. If you are not a coward, turn and speak to me.”

For the first time that day Finn’s eyes left the horizon. From atop the tall tower of stone, he turned and looked down upon the challenger. His eyes were firm and hard. He shifted his grip on his ash staff and held it with two hands. It was no meager weapon in the strong grip of a warrior. An ash staff could smash skulls as well as swords could split them.

“Speak your name, bold intruder,” the prince said in a firm voice.

“You know well who I am,” he replied.

“Well I do,” Finn answered, “but that all my people may know the name of him who challenges their prince, I charge you now to make yourself known.”

“Very well,” the intruder replied. “I am Réadban, son of Ramlaf. And I speak not to you alone, but to all of your people. Let them hear me if they will. We have waited long enough, and for nothing.”

To Deomaer’s great surprise, there actually arose some murmur of assent. Some felt they had been kept waiting all too long for the feast and celebration.

“You make us wait in vain for your proud lies. There will be no marriage,” Réadban continued. “Nor will there be a High King’s torc for your neck. No claim does the tribe of Folcwalda have upon the throne of Friesland.”

“Do you have greater claim?” Finn asked, his voice lowering dangerously. His hard eyes narrowed, and the grip upon his staff tightened. “If you do, then make it now.”

“No claim does anyone have to rule our clan save our chieftain alone,” the proud stranger answered. “We make no claim to rule over you, but we will have no High King for ourselves.”

“So you may choose. But it remains still to be seen.”

“No! It is not still to be seen. We have waited long enough. We wait no longer. You promise the support of Danish spears, but we see them not. And when we do, they will likely be piercing our shields.” At these words a number of Finn’s folk nodded. Many had feared the dreaded Danes for some time and had no desire to see them in their own village. Réadban was wisely playing on the villagers’ fears as well as their impatience, seeking to gain their support. “If you will make claim, then make it now by facing my sword. He is a coward who trusts in the spears of others. Prove your worth with your own sword! Will you face me alone, or need I call upon my warband to bring you down from your feeble tower?”

Haughty words Réadban spoke, seeking to anger Finn into accepting his challenge. For many days he had watched and waited in hiding, hoping that the Danes would not arrive and that he would have opportunity of carrying out his plans. Many secret ambitions he harbored in his heart. Despite his words, he hoped one day to have the Frisian throne himself. He knew well that if the Danes arrived and Finn and Hildeburh were wed, he himself would have little hope of ever opposing them. And in truth, though he told the waiting people to the contrary, he suspected that the Danes would indeed come, and soon. That was why he was acting now and taking his chance. If Finn was dead, there could be no marriage. Even if afterwards Réadban had to flee for his life to escape the vengeance of Finn’s kin, he would survive and return to power later. All the better if Friesland was in turmoil and had no prince. But he needed to provoke Finn to a fight if his plan was to succeed. Further, he needed to defeat him.

“Fool,” Finn spoke, “you contradict yourself even as you speak. You say that my promises are false and the Danes will not come, and then you warn us that the Danes will come and will be our enemies. You cannot have both! And you are twice a fool if you think to threaten me with your warband.” In one swift move he pulled his horn to his lips, and Réadban stepped back suddenly as if the ivory were a strung bow. But Finn did not wind it. “If this horn were sounded, in but little more time than it would take me to kill you, the warband of Folcwalda would be upon this hill and not one of your men would ride from Hwitstan alive. If a single man takes but one step closer, none shall live to see tomorrow.”

“Are you a coward then?” Réadban shouted. But he knew at once that his plan was falling. He knew Finn was right. If he could not anger the prince, then he could not defeat him. And his warband could not fight against Folcwalda’s. Even now, men in the village were looking up at them and wondering. Some were picking up their spears and swords. He shouted again in desperation, “Come down. I challenge you again. Come and prove your own sword.” But with his neck craned up to see Finn, he felt much less threatening than he would have liked.

“Your challenge I will accept,” Finn answered clearly and without hesitation.

Réadban’s face revealed his surprise at the prince’s response. And then it showed his fear. For as much as he had hoped that his plan to provoke Finn would succeed, he hoped also that it would fail. He had seen Finn wield a sword and was afraid to meet him in battle. Had he truly thought his plan would succeed, he might have been less willing to try.

But Réadban’s surprise and fear were the next moment replaced with rage when Finn continued, “If you persist in being a fool, I will accept your challenge, but you will wait until your head has cooled. Seven days hence you may appear before me and face my sword if you will. Then shall nobody stand between us. This day I will raise no weapon, for it is the day of my wedding.”

“Seven days I will not wait,” Réadban began to reply, but Finn interrupted him.

“Seven days you will wait. For when you see the Danes arrive according to my word, you may yet repent of your accusations. On that day you may bow and swear fealty to the king, or face judgment for the offense given me this day. For I account the offense of your insults to be great! Until that day I will hear no more. But in this I warn you: move not one man from where they stand or you shall all be struck down and your bodies sent to the pit!”

So fiercely spoken were Finn’s words that his challenger stepped back as if struck. He glared angrily up at the prince, but either he could think of nothing to say or he thought better of saying it. A long silence followed in which neither Finn nor Réadban spoke. Réadban stood seething, but did not move. Those around watched in stunned amazement at what had taken place. Very slowly Finn turned back to face the sea. His people followed his example, each making a conscious effort not to look at Réadban, though all were curious what he would do next. The angered young chieftain lowered his sword to the ground and fumed, but he made to move either to leave or to call his war band. He joined those waiting, hoping furiously that the Danes would not come and that Finn would be humbled.

Moments later the clear tone of Finn’s ivory horn sounded forth from the top of the hill and was heard for the first time in Friesland: a long, beautifully clear sound ringing from the tower overhead. In later years the mighty horn of Finn would be heard many times, bringing joy to the ears of his followers and fear to his enemies. But now it brought fear to Deomaer, for the moment he heard it and realized what it was he thought the worst—that Réadban’s warband was sweeping down upon the unarmed villagers and Finn was signaling for help. Little did it matter that Folcwalda would soon be there to avenge them. Deomaer would be dead within seconds. But when he turned to look, neither Réadban nor his warband had moved. Then why had the horn been winded?

There could be only one other reason: the Danish ship had been sighted.

Before Finn’s horn had finished ringing, Folcwalda appeared from out of Hwitstanburg followed by his thanes. His long strides carried him quickly up the hill, and in a few short moments he was standing beside the tower atop the hill with his thanes beside him. Ulestan stood on his right and the brothers Eormen and Edmen on his left. They were flanked closely by Aelfer, Beow, Froda and Hereric the Geat. Some others stood beside these on both sides or followed at a little distance. There were twenty thanes in all; twenty-two mighty Frisians, each with their own warbands and retinue. They were a fearsome band, armed and war ready, veterans all of many battles. And as mighty as his thanes appeared, Folcwalda was greater than all, both in strength and stature. Seeing him, it was clear how Folcwalda had been so quickly accepted as king. His kingship was visible in him. He was a chieftain among chieftains! And Finn also.

At their appearance, Réadban’s followers, who until then had remained astride their horses, dismounted and backed away nervously. Folcwalda glanced briefly at them once, and then longer at Réadban, but said nothing.

In the bright sun of the later afternoon Folcwalda, with his brazen boar’s-head helm and his bare sword which dangled at his side, glittered as much as the sea before him. His blade was chipped, scraped and scratched in a dozen places. And as badly battle-scarred as his sword was, the boar’s-head helmet was worse! What those blows which had so dented that metal would have done to Folcwalda’s head had he not been wearing the helmet, none would desire to guess. The king’s arms too were bare and as covered with scars as the blade which they held. Both hands were missing parts of fingers. Many who saw him were amazed that so many scars could appear on a man who was still alive. But the dents on the helmet and sword were testimony to the blows which had missed him.

Then Finn strode forth from the tower to stand at the side of his father. He appeared quite in contrast to Folcwalda. His sword was wrapped tightly in leather and was still draped over his back. He wore no helmet upon his head, but his hair flowed freely down over his neck and shoulders. Rather than a leather breast plate as his father wore, he had his red, sleeveless tunic with green patches on the shoulders and a blue silk belt. Only the covered sword gave hint to the warrior that Finn was. But even unarmed he looked nearly as formidable as his father. Surely these two would daunt the mightiest of warriors. Even the Danes would have to respect twenty-two Frisians such as those collected here!

Deomaer the jeweler looked again at the thanes collected behind the king. Eormen and Edmen, the strong and impetuous duo, had been the first to stand beside Folcwalda in his early days. These brothers were rash and adventurous, but loyal to the bone. They were hardy in battle, so Deomaer was told. In their youth they had acquired much fame and many enemies. Aelfer and his cousin Beow were the quiet ones. They carried spears—an idea they had borrowed from the Danes—and Roman short swords rather than the traditional broadswords of the Frisians. Froda was the youngest of Folcwalda’s thanes, and but a little older than Finn. He was no chieftain himself, but a cousin of Lynd, the chieftain of a large clan in the far southwest. Only five men and six horses were counted in his warband. Nonetheless, though he was not as powerful as the others and commanded no large host, Froda was a good friend of Finn and would likely prove to be his strongest supporter when the time came for the passing of the kingship. The two had traveled much together. Froda had only recently returned from wars in the east between the Geats and Swedes, where he had won much glory and was given noble gifts. To Folcwalda in turn he gave those gifts, including four tall war horses, pledging his allegiance once again with humble words to his king. He was a good thane who sought not for his independence.

Hereric the Geat was the enigma of Folcwalda’s hearthwerod. He had pledged himself to Folcwalda only two years ago after fleeing the land of the Geats for a reason none but he him self knew. Some rumored that he was a descendant of the evil Heremod the Dane. Heremod had sought refuge among the Jutes many years ago after slaying his own kinsmen. The Jutes had not only refused his request for refuge, but had killed him and sent his body back to the Danes. That was little more than rumor now, a tale told by poets around the mead benches. If there was any resemblance between Hereric and Heremod, nobody was alive to know. To Deomaer, Hereric didn’t seem like a kinslayer. He was calm and quiet, almost meek. He never spoke of fighting, nor did he even take place in the wild boar hunts. He carried himself about Hwitstan with great humility for one so close to the king. Only in battle did he show himself to be bold. Yet battle was something rarely seen in Friesland, aside from occasional small skirmishes and raids along the southwestern and eastern borders. Most of Folcwalda’s thanes who had seen battle had seen it else where.

Of all Folcwalda’s thanes, Ulestan the Wise was the most honored. He bore the family emblem of an owl on his shield and helm, and was called “The Owl” because of his great wisdom. The king knew and trusted that wisdom. It was rare to see Folcwalda anywhere without Ulestan at his right side. The two were like brothers. In his youth Ulestan had married Folcwalda’s younger sister Fealla. A year later she had miscarried and died. Though their time together was short, Ulestan’s love for Fealla had been so great that he had never taken another wife for himself, though Folcwalda’s other sister Ingwa had been offered to him. Deomaer knew nothing of Ulestan’s kinship, but he knew it to be noble since both Fealla and Ingwa had been offered to him.

Ulestan, Aelfer, Eormen, Edmen, Beow, Froda and Hereric stood with Folcwalda now—the closest and most trusted of Folcwalda’s thanes. Following these thanes up the hill were many of their retinue, the members of their warbands. Last came Daelga the poet. His jubilant laughter could be heard by all as he ascended the hill. As eager was he to witness great events as to sing of them. In his lifetime he had already seen much and would bear witness to much more—tales both of joy and of sorrow.

“Eormen,” Folcwalda said when the Danish ship had come into full view and moved toward the landing.

“Yes, lord,” the thane answered with a slight bow and bend of his knee.

“Extend to our guests the hospitality of this land. See that they are treated well.”

“Your wish,” he responded with a smile and a nod.

“Ulestan,” Folcwalda continued, the edges of his lip curling slightly in a concealed smile as he did so, “accompany Eormen to see that he doesn’t start a war with our future allies.”

Eormen’s answering smile was unconcealed. “You underestimate me, Lord Folcwalda. There are too few of them. I would wait until we were outnumbered by fifty or two fifties before I tried to begin a war.”

Folcwalda laughed. His thane was probably not very far from the truth. “Yes, you are quite right. Nonetheless, Ulestan will accompany you and see that our guests receive a proper welcome.”

Ulestan nodded, and the two proceeded down the slope to the beach followed by ten other armed warriors who stood close by. The children had all retreated back to the village long before Finn’s horn sounded, and the beach was almost empty when the Danish ship began to ride the low surf up to the sand.

“Aelfer and Edmen …”

“Yes,” they responded in unison.

“Remain with Finn. The rest of us will return to the hall.” “My lord?” Finn asked in surprise.

“It is fitting for a king to greet his guests from his hall,” Folcwalda answered. “You may remain here to greet your future bride and escort the Danes to the hall which will someday be yours.” He looked his son squarely in the eyes as he continued, “Bear yourself with pride today, Prince of Friesland. This marks the beginning of a great kingdom which will soon be yours.”

“Not too soon,” Finn said smiling in return. Then he turned to watch the incoming ship. “What have we here?” he suddenly exclaimed.

Folcwalda turned and gazed upon the beach to see what had caught his son’s attention. A second and third Danish ship had just come around the point and were now rowing into the cove. “Two more Danish ships?” Finn asked rhetorically. “They must have sixty warriors with them. Is this a wedding or an attack?”

A brief look of surprise and perhaps even doubt crossed Folcwalda’s visage. It remained there only a second, and then the look of resolute calm which was much more familiar was restored. “Froda, Hereric and Beow,” he commanded, “join Ulestan and Eormen on the beach. The rest of you return with me to the hall where we will greet our honored guests as a king should.” He turned and began down the hill back toward Hwitstanburg. As if nothing more than a parting thought, he added to Finn, “You have your horn should you for any reason need me.” Then he disappeared over the crest, followed by the few thanes not assigned to other tasks.

Finn turned again to face the Danes. The first ship had slid neatly onto the beach. There was a brief interchange between Ulestan and one of the Danes as they stepped forth. Deomaer did not know for sure who they were, but his guess was verified a second later as he overheard Finn talking to Edmen and Aelfer. “That is Hnaef, son of Hoc, a good prince … and Hengest, his loyal thane, after him. Oslaf the Jute follows next. Though he is no Dane, he holds some kinship with Hnaef. For more than a lifetime Jutland and his folk have been ruled by the Danes. There is some enmity between Jutish and Danish blood. I do not recognize the two who follow Oslaf, but they bear the same shield boss and helm. I would guess them to be Oslaf’s brothers—Guthlaf the elder and Hunlaf the younger.”

Then Finn’s voice faded in the wind, and Deomaer couldn’t hear what was said next. Two more armed Danes stepped from the ship and were followed immediately by an older Dane who, from his stature and bearing and from the way he was treated by both Ulestan and the other Danes, could only have been Hoc himself. Hoc was tall and broad, old, wise, proud; a king if Deomaer had ever seen one. He alone of all the Danes, save his daughter, wore no helmet. His white hair flowed out in a single braid reaching halfway down his back. If his appearance from afar was not utterly deceiving, he was taller even than Finn or Folcwalda. He towered even over his own son Hnaef. Stepping from the ship, he reached behind him and, to the joy of Finn, offered his hand to a waiting Hildeburh, who rose from her seat and stepped onto Frisian soil for the first time.

Deomaer could almost feel the ground shake from the great leap which Finn’s heart took as his future bride stepped ashore. Her beauty was no less than Finn himself had described it. She was certainly a treasure. For the first time Deomaer doubted the worth of the gifts he had made for her. As she ascended the hill to the waiting Finn, her beauty seemed to grow with each step. Deomaer stood transfixed by her eyes, as did Edmen and Aelfer. Only Finn was able to step forth. It was to him that her loving gaze was directed. Even as Finn moved to greet her, Hoc and Hnaef stepped ahead of her and intercepted him.

“Peace, Finn,” the Danish king said, raising his hand in greeting.

“Welcome, Hoc, king of the Danes,” Finn replied, pulling his gaze off his beloved only with great difficulty. “Your presence honors us and is much awaited.” He avoided the temptation to look past the king at his daughter, though he knew her eyes were on him.

“We welcome you also, Hnaef, son of Hoc,” Finn continued, addressing the other prince. He extended his hand, and they grasped each other by the wrists.

“It has been long,” Hnaef replied.

“Too long,” Finn said, smiling.

“Where is Folcwalda?” Hoc asked.

“He awaits you in his hall,” Finn answered. He wondered how they would respond to Hwitstanburg.

“Friesland is graced with a new hall?” came a voice from behind Hnaef. It was the one Finn had identified as Oslaf. From this close Deomaer had a much better view of him. He was about the same height as Deomaer, but broader and sturdier. He held a single spear in his right hand, and his left was hooked on a small purse hanging at his side. From head to foot he was decorated with silk. A red silk band was wrapped around each arm and another around his waist. A purple silk ribbon hung from his spear, and another was braided in his hair. There was even green silk on his leggings. How proud he must be, Deomaer thought, that he wears more silk than his king. Hoc wore only a single, thin strand of the precious material around the bottom of his braid. Oslaf’s brothers Hunlaf and Guthlaf were dressed in fashion similar to Oslaf. “And will there be treasure-giving at this hall?” Oslaf asked. Deomaer thought there was a great deal of arrogance in his voice. Perhaps Hnaef thought so as well because he quickly motioned Oslaf to silence.

Finn said nothing for some time, apparently wondering whether he should answer Oslaf or address only the king and the prince. He kept his eyes fixed’ on Hoc. When neither he nor Hnaef said anything, Finn chose to answer Oslaf. “As you shall soon see, Folcwalda is a generous king. Rings are given freely in Hwitstan.” As he said this, he glanced past Oslaf down to the beach. The two other Danish ships had pulled ashore, and there seemed to be some trouble between the Danes and the Frisian guards. “Ulestan, see to welcoming the rest of the Danes,” Finn said, nodding toward the beach.

Ulestan had already noticed the situation and was whispering something in Eormen’s ear. “Yes, lord,” he replied. “l will provide shelter for them in the outlying homes and see that their ships and weapons are well looked after while they are our guests.”

“Wisely done,” Finn said catching the meaning behind Ulestan’s words. He turned back to address Hoc, and his glance once again caught Hildeburh’s. They held one another’s gaze for a brief moment, and then Finn motioned to Hoc and Hnaef. “The day is late, and the pigs are on the spit. This is Summer’s Day. Mead and beer flow freely. Come and enjoy the hospitality of Hwitstan and all of Friesland.”

“We are honored,” Hoc replied and motioned to his own thanes to follow him.

Deomaer watched as Finn, Hoc, Hnaef and Hildeburh started down the hill toward the hall at Hwitstan. Aelfer and Edmen followed closely behind Finn. Hengest remained close behind Hnaef. Guthlaf, Oslaf and Hunlaf followed at a distance and talked quietly among themselves, occasionally pointing toward something they saw off to one side or another. The jeweler then turned back toward the beach. The turmoil seemed to have subsided as soon as Ulestan arrived, and he and Eormen were now leading a small company of Danes up the hill. The remainder of the Danes, some thirty or so men, stayed with the Danish ships under the watchful eye of the ten Frisian guards who remained behind.

Deomaer walked briskly and entered the hall only a few paces behind the last of the Danes. Most of the village was gathered outside, wandering about and trying to look busy while hoping to catch a glimpse of what was taking place inside. To them this hall was the symbol of the new importance of Hwitstan. When work on the hall had begun, the village had suddenly grown to almost three times its normal size. This growth could only be attributed to the hall, they thought. And from the moment it had been completed, chieftains and thanes from across Friesland had not ceased entering and leaving its doors. And now the Danish king himself, a giant in their eyes, had entered the hall. Imaginations ran wild with pictures of kings conjuring spirits and casting spells or performing elaborate rituals; or of fights to the death between the Frisians and Danes over the treasures given by the two kings. The truth, Deomaer knew, would be much more mundane. He already had a good guess what would happen: there would a be a rather long ceremonial greeting followed by some giving of gifts—mostly gold and silver rings and pendants crafted by Deomaer himself. If Folcwalda were gathered with his own thanes only, the gifts would have included ancient and proven swords, spears, and all forms of war gear. But these gifts of time-honored weapons would not be likely today. It would be foolish to give a trusted sword to someone who might someday use it against you. Following the gift giving, there would probably be a more private interchange between the kings and princes. Then the wedding and Summer’s Day celebration would begin.

Despite the villagers’ imaginations of the glories of a mighty king inside his hall, in the best of times a hall was more of a home—a place for shared story and drink, for friendship and comradeship among the loyal followers of a chieftain—than it was a place where great plans were laid and daring challenges issued. It was true that in times of war a king would gather his thanes in a hall and fill them with brave words of noble deeds, would speak of life and death, of fear and courage. But a hall was also the place where warriors would return after a war to find peace—a warm fire, a mug of mead and fellowship—the things most worth going to war for and the things which made returning most worthwhile. The mystery surrounding a hall added to the awe the villagers had of those who entered, but little of that mystery was grounded in truth.

Nonetheless, as Deomaer strode past the villagers he felt a certain pride that he was among those who were allowed to enter. Inside were gathered the Danes and those whom Deomaer called the “important” Frisians: the thanes and retainers of Finn and Folcwalda and a few others, such as Deomaer himself and the poet Daelga—those who had some special position of honor within the village. Deomaer wasn’t sure if he had been given a place within the hall because of his work as jeweler and moneyer or because of his common, though distant, ancestry with the king. He hoped it was because of his work.

“Warriors all, save us alone,” Daelga whispered in his ear, catching him by surprise and making him jump. “Common men we, with kings to dine.” Before Deomaer could respond, the poet was gone. Was his awe that visible as he looked around him? Or was Daelga, too, able to read his thoughts?

The jeweler slid onto a bench near the door and watched as Hoc approached Folcwalda’s bench. He had appeared merely tall while standing outside. Inside the hall he was a veritable giant. Some of Folcwalda’s mightiest armed men looked puny in comparison. On one side of Hoc walked the smaller Hnaef, still a large man by any measure. On Hoe’s other side came Hildeburh, holding firmly to his extended arm. Her face revealed her timidity and modesty, but there was no fear in her expression. Hengest, Oslaf, Guthlaf and Hunlaf walked a few paces behind their king, and the rest of the Danes dispersed into the hall in groups of three or four, making room for themselves among the Frisians. Hoc held everyone’s attention. As he approached Folcwalda’s throne, the Frisian king rose to greet him. ,

“Hail Hoc, son of Heart, descendant of the gods. Welcome to Hwitstan and Friesland. May your journey have started in peace, and may it end in peace. Hail Hnaef, son of Hoc. May your name one day be as honored as your father’s, and may your hand be as generous. Hail Hildeburh. May your name be forever praised among the Frisians as was your mother’s among the Danes. May you be a fruitful vine,” he continued with a wink, “growing in fertile soil. Welcome to our family.”

So saying, Folcwalda extended his arm in greeting. His bearing was strong and confident. For some reason Hoe’s stature did not dominate Folcwalda’s as it had the others’. Though the Danish king was taller even than Folcwalda, something about the Frisian king—his manner perhaps, or his strength, or the way he held his arms or shoulders, or simply his air of confidence enabled him to stand undaunted beside the giant of a Danish king. They stood as equals. Deomaer found this very reassuring. He was intimidated by the Danes, but Folcwalda’s bearing and manner gave him courage. A good king inspired hope in the hearts of his people.

During this greeting, Finn had stepped to the side of his father. His gaze was now freely fixed upon Hildeburh, and she returned it openly.

“Greetings, Folcwalda, son of Folgar,” Hoc replied. “May your kingdom last forever. Your welcome does us great honor. May we return that welcome in our halls. Peace to you and your hall. May we leave with the same peace that we brought.”

Folcwalda bowed his head slightly and removed from his neck a magnificent gold torc decorated with garnets and surrounded by a twisting silver wire. Deomaer beamed with pride at his own workmanship as his king placed the gift in the hands of Hoc. “May this always be light upon your neck, and may the head that wears it never be cloven.”

“May the hands of the giver be as blessed as those of him who received,” Hoc returned, bending the torc around his own neck.

Then Finn stepped forward and approached Hnaef. “May your reign be as mighty and long-lasting as your father’s.” He removed the golden boar’s head from the top of his staff and presented it to the prince. “May your staff never break,” he concluded.

Hnaef likewise clasped the hand of Finn. “May our nations as well as their princes be as brothers, and may your staff once again suffer from the weight of too much gold.”

Then Oslaf coughed rather loudly and took a slight step forward. Deomaer noticed that both he and his brothers had their hands resting lightly on the hilts of their swords. Are they expecting gifts as well? he wondered. At the same time that Oslaf was seeking attention, Ulestan entered the hall leading a large group of Danes from the second and third ships. The Danes proceeded to disperse into the hall. There was no small bit of elbowing and pushing as they made room for themselves. Neither of the kings or princes seemed to notice either Oslaf or the new disturbance, and Deomaer wondered if they would. Ulestan quietly made his way to the front of the hall, where he stood a few paces behind Folcwalda. The dialogue between the kings continued, and the hall soon settled as all eyes and ears focused on them once again.

“In return,” Hoc continued, “we bring to you the greatest treasure in the land of the Danes.” Taking a step forward, he placed his daughter’s hand on the arm of Finn. She squeezed it gently, and Finn placed his free hand on top of hers. “It is not without sorrow that our land parts with its chief source of beauty,” Hoc continued. “May you treat her well and preserve the peace that is now between us. It would not go well for an ill hand to touch a daughter of the Danes.”

“Nor would it go well,” Folcwalda answered sternly, “for an ill hand to touch the wife of a Frisian king.”

“Finn, son of Folcwalda …” Hoc began to say, turning toward the Frisian prince. But whatever he was going to say he never finished. A deep, lighthearted laugh bellowed from the old king as soon as he looked at his daughter. She had already slid under Finn’s arm and was gazing longingly at him, oblivious to the situation around them.

Folcwalda and Hnaef both caught Hoc’s laughter, and it soon spread throughout the hall. Though most of those present didn’t know the reason for the sudden outburst of gaiety, they were quick to join. The tension which had been building suddenly eased out of the room like a receding tide. Finn and Hildeburh both looked up and blushed, but joined in the laughter.

“Enough,” Folcwalda finally bellowed. “Let the feast begin. We have much to celebrate this Summer’s Day, not the least of which is the joining of Finn and Hildeburh. Let them lead the way.”

Finn grabbed Hildeburh’s hand tightly and almost whisked her out of the hall through a mob of Frisians and Danes who parted to make room for them and cheered them on as they went. When they stepped out of the hall, a huge roar of applause and greeting arose from the village. Those who were waiting outside joined the cheering for the prince and his bride-to-be. Hildeburh held to the prince, and he never let go of her but once for the rest of the day and night.

Then began the feasting all had waited for. Though the boars were still roasting, there was a great enough abundance of other fare to make men happy.

The hall soon began to empty, though the two kings remained. A second bench had been placed next to Folcwalda’s as a place of honor for Hoc. The two now sat side by side as if they were old friends—and maybe they were for all Deomaer knew.

“Why three ships and such a large warband?” Deomaer heard Folcwalda ask as the jeweler tarried just a moment behind the throng.

“Ah, that is nothing,” Hoc replied. “It was only at the urging of Oslaf and his brothers. They thought it would be safer in the case of unforeseen events.”

“Unforeseen events?” Folcwalda laughed. “Since when has anything ever taken Hoc by surprise? And who would dare to attack any Danish band, no matter how small?”

“Yes, I know.” The Danish king sighed. “But as I grow older, I am afraid I grow more easily swayed by my thanes. Hunlaf can be very persistent. Let us not allow that to be a thorn between us. We have much else to discuss, not the least of which are the kingdoms which are gaining power in the south.”

“The Merovingians!” Folcwalda spat.

V

The Lay of Folcwalda

Deomaer turned and walked out of the hall. The sight outside was almost overwhelming. The mead was already flowing freely, and the Danes and Frisians were laughing and hugging as if they were brothers. Children ran in and out everywhere, for the most part ignored by their parents and older siblings. Most of the celebration took place in the large clearing to the north of the hall, on the seaward side of the village. Scattered about the edges of the clearing, many of the younger warriors took part in a myriad of athletic contests. There were sword fights played with mock swords of leather-covered wood, stone-throwing events, wrestling contests, and many other games of skill and strength. All this went on for some time.

Then once more Finn’s horn was sounded. All the village turned to look toward the hall from whence the sound had come. There beside the great ash stump stood Folcwalda’s poet. In a single, twisting leap Daelga was atop the stump, harp in hand. With eyes greener than the leaves of the ash beside him, and light curly hair that fell to his shoulders, he could have been a boy of fifteen summers. But he was ageless. His thin frame belied the strength in his wiry muscles. And his eyes, green and alive in the summer sunlight, could turn suddenly grey beside the winter hearth fire and pass through a man like the fell north wind. Two generations of kings he had served already, and a third would follow. Bard, scop, poet—whatever one would call him, he sang and men listened.

“With strength of twelve,
Of twenty, the mighty,

Wise Folcwalda,
Friesland’s good lord.

To Swedeland’s shores
He sailed alone,

The Swan Road crossed,
Sea’s icy waves.

With courage bold
There brave deeds did;

A prince he left,
Returned a king.”

So began Daelga to sing a tale of the mighty deeds of the king. “Folcwalda the Fair” this king was called—the son of Folgar, the lord of his folk, the hawk. Many brave deeds and feats did Folcwalda accomplish to win his throne, but none earned him more glory than the recapture of his father’s golden tore. This tale Daelga now told, and men and women drew near to listen. Though all but a few in Friesland had heard the tale before, yet such was Folcwalda’s fame and Daelga’s gift that they listened readily. And there were others besides, king and thanes from many kingdoms who had come to celebrate the wedding of Folcwalda’s son Finn. They would do well to hear of the wisdom and strength of the new Frisian king.

Folcwalda had been a young prince, not yet able to sit astride a horse, when the Swedes led by Ongintheo had come raiding along Friesland’s coast. Six and ten ships, fifteen spears each, sought the plunder of war. As swift as birds’ flight, they appeared seemingly from nowhere and were gone, and none could stand against them. Villages were burned which would not pay the ransom, and Frisian women and children were killed or taken as slaves. When the rumor of these raids reached Folgar, and the smoke from surrounding villages clouded the sky, he raised what small warband he could to stand against the Swedes. For though his clan was small he was a proud king, and he would pay no ransom. It was not many days before they came, and when they did a battle was waged. The king and his small Frisian clan fought valiantly to defend their village, but the fight was in vain. The Swedish warband was far too great. Though he stood and fought until the end, Folgar was finally killed and the golden torc taken from his neck by Ongintheo himself. However, Folcwalda his son was neither killed nor taken captive. At the command of Folgar, an old and wise thane had hidden the prince in the hills. There, from his vantage atop a rocky slope, Folcwalda watched the entire battle. With the eyes of a hawk he saw all that took place, and in the hour his father fell he swore he would one day recover the tore.

Tall and strong grew Folcwalda, and fair to gaze upon, but grim was his mood and fiercely determined his spirit. Weak was the old thane who had saved him, barely able even to walk in his old age, but no greater warrior had ever lived in the lands of the Frisians. He taught Folcwalda well. No sooner could he hold a sword, but Folcwalda was swinging it mightily. No sooner could he hold a spear, but he was already wielding it like the veteran of many wars. Like a wild boar he was, and none could restrain him or dissuade him from his purposes. When the old thane died, Folcwalda would wait no longer. With spear, sword and shield he set out alone for the land of the Swedes, seeking to reconquer his father’s torc and avenge his father’s blood. Many were they who would have traveled with him had he asked. Sons and brothers they were of the thanes who had fallen with Folgar, and they desired vengeance upon the Swedes. But Folcwalda knew it not. For one man to attempt the seas alone was no small feat itself. But neither wild winds, nor high waves, nor the icy waters of the bight daunted him, for fate led him on. He sailed northward to the lands of the Angles. When his food gave out and his sail tore, he abandoned his ship and turned inland. He crossed the Angles’ land to the great Baltic Sea and the burg of Schleswig, where the name of his father was known among the people. They gave him a new ship and provisions for many new days, and he pressed on eastward.

Shelter he found in the lands of the Danes, and fast friendship was quick made with Hoc, their young king. Many promises and vows they exchanged, and they swore to uphold each other in war should Folcwalda ever become king. But despite Hoc’s words to dissuade him, Folcwalda would not stay. His voyage was soon resumed, and none of the people of the Danes thought to see him again. Yet one gift Hoc gave him at his parting, and that served him well. A proud and hard helm was forged for him in the Danish smithies, and ever after, to the end of his days, Folcwalda wore that helm whenever he rode to battle.

Onward he traveled. Northward from the land of the Danes he sailed to the Geatish shores. A home he could have found there too had he desired, for their king was old and he looked upon Folcwalda as a son. And the Geatish people loved him as well and gladly would have had him for a prince, for he was tall and fair to look upon. Nor did they have any great love for the Swedes who had done them as great harm as they had done to Folcwalda. The Battle-Scyldings they called the Swedes, and they were bitter enemies. There in the Geatish hall of King Hrethmond, another treasure was given to Folcwalda of greater value than countless rings or jewels: an old war sword of wound steel, worn by the Geatish king in the days of his youth. Proven in battle times without count, it would not fail a steady hand. Folcwalda received it gratefully and laid his own blade aside. But he sought not a treasure-giver, nor did he desire a home. He sought only the golden torc that had been his father’s. A few days only he remained among the Geats, gathering his strength and readying for what lay ahead. Brave words he heard at his parting, and proud rings and treasure he was promised if he returned. Then the wind filled his sails once again.

It was no weary sailor who arrived in Swedeland, but rather a prince strengthened by his long journey and hardened by his days at sea. The determination which kindled his spirit had risen to a roaring flame. He cared not if he died in his quest, but he would live not a day longer without his father’s tore. He set helm on head and shield on arm and strode confidently to the hall of the king. Such was the fierceness in Folcwalda’s glance and the strength in his muscles, and so great his stature, that though he had never swung blade in battle he appeared to those who saw him a mighty warrior. Men fell away before him.

Now, the time of his arrival was early summer when the Swedish kings were gathering at their summer halls beside the sea from where they could carry on their wars and raids more easily. Ongintheo had once more gathered his warband about him and was preparing to set sail. Had Folcwalda arrived with his own warband, he would never have seen the inside of Ongintheo’s hall, for the Swedish king’s warband would have met him on the beach and a battle would have been waged there. But Ongintheo sat outside his hall and, seeing Folcwalda approaching alone, thought him no threat. When the young Frisian prince placed his helm on his head, the Swedish king laughed aloud. “Does this one come alone seeking war?” he jeered.

But the laughter died in his throat when Folcwalda spoke. “I am Folcwalda, son of Folgar and rightful owner of the torc about your neck. Will Ongintheo, the honored king of the Battle-Scyldings, fight with me, or will he hide like a Swedish dog?”

Dead silence fell upon those who heard these words. Venom dripped from Folcwalda’s mouth. Long had he pondered how he might challenge Ongintheo, and he had chosen well. His words cut a deep wound and then poisoned it.

A look of fear crossed Ongintheo’s face. He knew nothing of Folcwalda, but could see that the boy had the strength of a giant. He had no desire to fight him. But neither was Ongintheo a coward, and strong words had been spoken. Kings did not come by their kingship easily, and many a Swedish throne had been lost because a bold thane saw a weakness in their treasure-giver. Ongintheo could not allow his thanes to see him refuse so bold a challenge. And that was Folcwalda’s only hope, for he could not face Ongintheo’s entire warband alone.

“Come, take the tore,” Ongintheo replied as he rose to his feet. “Cut it from my neck if you will.”

The words were hardly from his mouth before his sword was whirring down on Folcwalda’s head. The Frisian prince was unprepared. He was no battle-hardened warrior, and though he had been taught well he was untried. Only at the last moment did he raise his own blade to counter his enemy’s blow. Ongintheo’s blade caught his own, knocked it back, and then came down upon his head. Had Folcwalda not been wearing the Danish helm, the battle would have ended at that moment. But the helm held strong, and Ongintheo’s blow, to the astonishment of both of them, glanced off.

Ongintheo, seeing Folcwalda’s youth and inexperience, pressed the attack. Folcwalda staggered backward, and Ongintheo swung his sword again. Folcwalda caught the blade on his shield. He tried to raise his own blade, but had no time. Another blow and then another he took with his shield. The blade bit deeply into the hard wood. Folcwalda managed a weak swipe at Ongintheo’s legs, but the Swede brushed it aside with his own sword and swung again.

For a long time the battle raged such. It went ill for Folcwalda, but he kept himself alive. Nor did his strength diminish, for he was in the prime of his youth, and many days at sea had taught him a stamina which Ongintheo did not understand. Still, the Frisian prince could land no blow, and his shield was battered sorely. All the time he was forced backward. With each blow landed upon him, Ongintheo’s thanes cheered.

Then came the fiercest blow that Folcwalda had yet felt. It rattled his bones and jarred his arm. When he looked down, his shield was no more. A look of triumph filled Ongintheo’s face. But Folcwalda as yet knew no fear, for if he could not recover his father’s torc he preferred death. He cast aside the splinters and gripped his sword with two hands. Now every blow of his enemy meant his life, for if he failed to counter just one, it would surely finish him.

But Ongintheo was winded. And as Folcwalda continued to frustrate the attacks against him, a brief hint of fear appeared in his enemy’s face. The prince saw that fear, and for the first time he felt hope. A blow was dealt at his head. He stopped it and returned one. Ongintheo fell backward, and suddenly Folcwalda was on the attack. He advanced and swung his blade more fiercely. The Swede blocked the blow and staggered. The prince swung again with all his might, leveling a great two-handed swing. The blades met in midair. Only one held. The Geatish work did not fail; the blade of Ongintheo shattered.

A look of horror crossed the Swedish king’s face. Folcwalda paused for a moment. Ongintheo’s thanes saw all and started forward to protect their king. But they knew they would not be in time. Folcwalda’s blade was too quick.

Yet, the Frisian warrior did not swing. For at the same moment that the Swedish king’s blade shattered, a young child stepped forward among the ring of onlookers, and the unexpected movement caught Folcwalda’s eye. So much did the child look like the king that he could not have been other than his son. A vision flashed in Folcwalda’s mind of a young Frisian prince standing atop a rocky hill watching his father die.

Mercy stayed his hand. He lowered his blade and stepped back. Little understanding did Ongintheo have of Folcwalda’s actions, but relief and thankfulness filled his heart. That night the torc of Folgar was placed on Folcwalda’s neck by Ongintheo himself.

Daelga’s tale ended there after the recovery of the torc, but Folcwalda’s great feats had not. The king was known far and wide. With that act of mercy shown to the Swedish king wisdom had come to the young prince. Or perhaps wisdom had always been his and his mercy had been its first revelation. With his father’s torc about his neck, Folcwalda had returned from Swedeland to Friesland to begin an even greater work, one that would last his lifetime. He began to build a kingdom.

From the very first, when Folcwalda had gathered the chieftains of Friesland to be his thanes and united the villages under his rule, he had known what he was doing. It was no simple desire for power which prompted him to act. Folcwalda had understood that if the rest of the chieftains didn’t unite, Friesland could not stand against the Merovingians long. The other chieftains knew this as well, and though most were slow to act, Folcwalda was persistent and persuasive, and his arguments finally found ears. As a single kingdom, he told the chieftains, they could act as a unified force. And more important than their increased military might was the centralization of the trade customs and fees which were the source of income for most of Friesland. As a unified kingdom, the individual villages would stop competing against one another and would thus increase the profits of all the Frisian villages. At first only a few chieftains joined with Folcwalda. But each one who did added to the momentum and swayed others until there was a large following behind the future king. Those who were not easily persuaded by Folcwalda’s arguments were occasionally won by force. For among those who had early pledged themselves to Folcwalda were chieftains of the most powerful clans of Friesland. The brothers Eormen and Edmen, strong, mighty, hardheaded, and loyal, had alone persuaded many to follow a single king. Little use had those two chieftains for words. However, their swords spoke loudly.

Eventually all but a few villages in the more remote parts of the land had taken Folcwalda as their king. The Half-Franks, clans of mixed Frisian and Frankish blood dwelling at Wic by Dorestad on the Rhine and at Domburg at the mouth of the Meuse River, were the last major clans to bow to the king. And Lyndlaf, the son of Lynd, the chieftain of the Half-Franks at Dorestad, had already promised his allegiance in secret. He had asked only that his father be left alone to rule the village until his days ended. Folcwalda needed only wait until the death of Lynd, who was already quite old, and Wic by Dorestad would be part of the kingdom.

VI

The Winning of the Bride

When the Lay of Folcwalda had been finished, it came time for the chief event of the entire celebration: the winning of the bride. A high fenced pen had been erected on the west side of Hwitstanburg, and roaming about within was a wild boar. Angry at its captivity, it charged madly at any who came too close. Though a sturdy fence separated them from the beast, mighty warriors backed away quickly from its charges. They had too often seen what damage such a creature could do, even when caged.

While some taunted and further angered the boar, Finn was ushered to the far side of the pen where Hunlaf the Jute, familiar with the custom, handed him a cruel hooked spear. The prince knew what was required. A large crowd had gathered to watch. While the boar was kept occupied at the other end of the enclosure, the prince climbed over the wall and entered the arena where his right to manhood would be tested.

To the great distress of the women of Friesland, the challenge of the boar was a traditional rite of the wedding day. A few days before a wedding a wild boar would be captured and caged. It would be fed well for a day or two, but then left hungry the morning of the wedding to increase its aggressiveness. Of course, no boar needed to be left hungry to be dangerous. They were vicious creatures by birth. A single enraged boar could wreak havoc among an entire village before being captured or killed. With one lunge their powerful necks and knife-sharp tusks could rip a hole from a man’s knee all the way to his belly. No wolf pack or even a bear would fight the wild boar. It was a mighty beast, the bane of many lesser animals and of not few hunters. On more than one occasion victory had been won by a boar against a potential groom and the wedding celebration had been brought quickly and gloomily to an end. The wiser young men of the village would not drink the mead cup on their wedding day until after their encounter with the boar. Those who drank of the cup too soon did not usually fare well.

As Finn was a great warrior and the son of a chieftain, the village had found and captured a particularly ferocious boar. Two men had been injured caging it.

And now Finn was within its enclosure. Its hackles were raised as it turned to face him. Finally it had an opportunity to vent its fury, for an enemy had come within the cruel fence which encaged it. The mighty boar wasted no time. It lowered its tusks and charged with blood in its eyes—Finn’s blood.

Finn took a step forward, planted his feet firmly, lowered his spear, and braced himself. Seeing the spear, the boar veered at the last second and rushed past Finn, crashing into the fence behind him. Finn took a swipe as it passed and drew the first blood.

The boar felt the pain, and its anger increased. Circling to the far end of the pen, it charged a second time. Once again Finn leveled the spear-point at the creature’s heart. This time it did not turn away. The full force of the boar’s charge exploded into the point. The spear given him by Hunlaf proved too weak. The shaft shattered, and Finn tumbled over backwards, holding only splinters. Hildeburh shouted and started toward him, but was held back. Some thought the boar had been killed, others that Finn had been hurt by his fall. Neither was true. The prince appeared stunned, but he was uninjured. And though the spear-point had impaled itself deeply into the boar’s front leg, the beast was by no means finished. Finn rolled quickly to his feet as the boar approached him again.

The boar’s third approach was slower and more deliberate. Blood spilled from the wound in its leg, where the end of the spear was still protruding. Its eyes were fixed cruelly on its enemy’s belly. Finn unsheathed the great broadsword which hung on his back and lowered the point until it stood two inches from the boar’s snout. They stood for a few moments looking at each other. The boar’s huge nostrils flared in and out in time with its heavy breathing. Finn’s visage was grim and determined. A sword was generally not a good weapon to use against a boar; it was too short, and there was no good way to brace it between yourself and your opponent. The boar seemed to sense Finn’s vulnerability as it lowered its head and stepped forward.

In the wink of an eye Finn raised his great blade a few feet and brought it down with all of his strength. The stroke went clean through the target, and the contest was over. The animal’s head rolled to the side. Its lifeblood pulsed forth in streams onto the ground. A few of the women who had already partaken of one too many cups of mead fainted. The rest of the crowd cheered.

Finn wiped off his blade, raised it high into the air in victory, and then resheathed it. Hildeburh was already running across the pen. She reached Finn and leapt into his arms. The crowd cheered again.

The cooks entered the pen and dragged the boar out behind the hall where the roasting pits were. A few seconds later, following tradition, they emerged again, carrying a boar that had been roasting all day. The cooked boar was brought to Finn as if it were the wild boar he had just killed. Finn was handed a knife, and he cut a large hunk of the meat. There were more cheers as he ripped off a huge bite with his teeth. Then, to the amusement of the onlookers, as the hot juices dripped down Finn’s chin, Hildeburh grabbed the knife from his hands and cut an equally large piece of the meat for herself. She bit into it even more savagely than Finn had. Though she didn’t know it at the time, she had just begun a new tradition in Friesland.

Once Finn had taken his bite, the feasting began in earnest. Three more of the roasts were carried out and set on huge wooden blocks outside the hall. From that point on, every man, woman and child ate as much as desired when desired.

From out of nowhere the poet Daelga suddenly appeared once more and jumped again onto the stump in the center of the clearing.

“Come, listen, and drink,” he proclaimed laughing as he strummed on his lyre. The commotion quieted quickly as more and more people noticed him. His reputation throughout Friesland was high, and his earlier singing of Folcwalda’s Lay had raised it.

“Come, hear, and enjoy,” he sang louder, still strumming. A few more gathered around the stump. Those closest to him sat down.

“Come, open your ears, and see what enters,” he said more quietly. Then, when he had a crowd large enough for his liking, he changed the strumming on his lyre and began to sing.

“Of dragons and demons
Daelga will sing;

Of ents, armies, edges,
Endings and death;

Of Saxons and Scyldings,
And Spear-Danes and Jutes;

Of battles and beasts,
Of beer, mead, and wine.

Now lays shall be lifted
With lyre and with voice;

Tales will be told;
Times past relived.

Your ears open wide
These words you will hear;

Of princes and pride
Poems will tell.

Of doubt, courage, duty
Daelga will sing.”

Without hesitation the poet once again changed his strum and immediately started into a whole series of poems and songs. He sang first of the creation of Middle-earth and of the wars between the ice giants and the gods. He followed with a song of Weland the smith, half-god and half-man; how he was imprisoned by the evil king Niphad who had him hamstrung to prevent his escape, and of how Weland gained his revenge by first killing Niphad’s two sons and then ravaging his daughter Beaduhild before flying away on man-made wings, leaving the evil king to die in anguish. He finished with the tale of how Weland finally returned to take Beaduhild for his wife and of the birth of their son, Widia the adventurer. Daelga continued with more tales of Friesland and Folcwalda. Then, to the delight of the gathered Danes, he sang of the legendary Danish king Scyld Scefing and the glory of the Spear-Danes of old. Their princes did brave deeds, and far and wide many tribes paid tribute to Scyld. His son Beow was famous as well, and his glory also spread quickly. Very few, if any, left before the tale was finished. Continuing in this vein and taking only a few breaks to refill his mead cup, the poet Daelga was able to continue entertaining until long after the sun had set.

Finn and Hildeburh listened long enough to hear the first part of a new poem about Folcwalda, which Daelga promised to continue the following night. Then the couple danced and drank until the last red of the sun dipped below the horizon. In accordance with the tradition, Finn then swept Hildeburh up in his arms and carried her around the entire village, ending at the new home he had built for her with his own hands. “The young princeling brags of the growth of the Hwitstan,” Deomaer overheard Hunlaf saying to his brothers as Finn turned the first corner, “but he will soon be cursing these ugly new huts when Hildeburh grows heavy in his arms.”

“You do not know our prince,” Deomaer replied under his breath. The jeweler was right. Finn began to sing and almost ran the final stretch, with Hildeburh holding on tightly and singing with him. Then, without a word, Finn swung into the hut, pulled the skins tightly over the entrance behind him, and was not seen again for two days.

VII

Farewells

The absence of Finn and Hildeburh did not lessen the enthusiasm of the celebration, which continued unabated late into the night until one by one the warriors sank into unconsciousness. Though most managed to find their way into Hwitstanburg where they collapsed on a bench or beside the hearth at the foot of their chieftain, more than a few spent the night outside on the ground.

Yet the mead was still plentiful, and the celebration of summer continued the following day and the day after as well. The Danes and Frisians were soon joined by many hale warriors from lands far and wide as numerous ships, proud and full, sailed into Hwitstanwic from across’ the Swan Road. They came bearing kings, princes, chieftains, thanes, earls and warriors alike. By Folcwalda’s invitation they had come to join the celebration and to witness the alliance of Danes and Frisians. Nor did those present lack opportunity to form alliances and treaties with other war leaders and clan chieftains who had also come. For that reason alone, many great chieftains had come or sent their princes and earls. And even those who had no wish or need for new alliances were drawn to the celebration for fear that if they were not present, they might find, in their absence, that their enemies had suddenly allied against them. Folcwalda, in his wisdom and cunning, had preyed upon these very motivations to gather together those powers whom he desired to witness his new bond with Hoc. Each king or prince whom he greeted was let to see very clearly the bench of the Danish king beside that of his own.

On the first night, Saxon and Swedish princes with their small warbands had arrived from opposite directions at the same time. Each eager to be first into the village, they had nearly run up the hill. The Saxons and Swedes were followed shortly by a band of English thanes with their young prince, no more than ten summers old. And early the following morning a ship bearing a grey and battle-hardened chieftain of a small Jutish tribe arrived. His battle-axe in hand, he stepped ashore appearing ready at any moment to enter into battle. He had no love for the Swedes, nor for the Danes, who ruled too much Jutish land. Only with great difficulty was he convinced there was no trap waiting to be sprung.

And so it continued throughout the celebration and for many days afterward. The Frisian guards at Hwitstanwic were kept busy that week. Fortunately for those in the village, the warbands were so concerned about the danger from each other that many of their men were left on the beach to guard their ships. Small camps spread out all along Hwitstanwic.

The chieftains, however, all found their way to Hwitstan, where they entered the new hall and were greeted warmly by Folcwalda and Hoc, who spent the greater portion of those three days sitting side by side on their new thrones. Neither king partook of the mead cup to any great extent, but neither did they discourage their followers from enjoying its pleasures.

Folcwalda took special interest in the arrival of Ecgwalda, the ruler of the Half-Franks of Domburg. Ecgwalda’s people were the only remaining Frisians not to accept Folcwalda’s kingship, save for the powerful clan at Wic by Dorestad. (But Lyndlaf, soon to be the chieftain at Dorestad, had already promised his allegiance. It was only a matter of time—months or maybe even days—until his father would die and pass on the crown.) Ecgwalda was the last obstacle to a completely unified Friesland. His small village of Domburg in the southwest was on a long peninsula near the mouth of the Meuse River, not far south of the Rhine. For most of its great length, the Meuse was deep and wide. It flowed into the North Sea from deep in the heart of the continent, making it one of the best trade routes in the north. Many goods destined for or coming from the English, Jutish and Saxon cities passed through Domburg, due east of Cantwara and not far from the narrowest point of crossing—a journey of no more than twenty miles. Thus, though Ecgwalda’s tribe was small, it was strong and wealthy. Furthermore, Domburg was easily defended. Its position on the end of the peninsula left only one narrow approach by land.

The village’s main weakness lay in the number of small islands scattered about the bay at the mouth of the Meuse. The islands could act as shelters for invading armies which might hide there, waiting to attack. Landings on most of these isles were fairly easy, leaving Domburg vulnerable to quick raids from the sea. Yet even the islands could be used to Domburg’s advantage if the clan’s chieftain planned well. Small outposts scattered about them would serve to give warning of attacks and could also be used to harry the ships of an invading army. Domburg could be built, by either Folcwalda or his enemies, into more than just the largest of Friesland’s trade centers. It could become a strong city as well. It was vital to the unity of Friesland to gain Ecgwalda’s allegiance, and to do so quickly and without shedding Frisian blood.

If forced to it, Folcwalda had the military might to conquer Ecgwalda and seize Domburg by force. Many of his thanes had suggested such more than once. In fact, a plan for doing so had been brewing in his mind for over a year. He refrained only because the growing Merovingian kingdom watched his every move closely. A war within Friesland would surely invite raids from the outside; if not from the Merovingians, then from overseas. Furthermore, Folcwalda loathed to shed the blood of his men unless it was necessary. Even so, he knew that failure to add Domburg to the kingdom soon would severely weaken Friesland’s dominance of the best trade routes.

Ulestan, too, was aware of the importance of Domburg and thus of Ecgwalda. When he saw the chieftain arrive, he made a point of gathering the best of the Frisian knights—those that could be found sober—to stand in the hall beside Folcwalda. Deomaer, from the back of the hall, watched with interest as Ulestan made every effort to display the might of his king to the visiting chieftain from Domburg. He noticed as well the way Ecgwalda looked upon Hoc with fear and respect. The new allegiance with the Danes was having its desired effect—at least upon Ecgwalda. Late on the second day of feasting, Ecgwalda approached Folcwalda and said a few words which only Ulestan and Hoc were close enough to hear. Folcwalda rose to his feet, and the two stared at each other for a few moments and then smiled as they extended hands and grasped each other by the wrists. Whatever had transpired bode well for Friesland. Ulestan disappeared shortly after that, satisfied that his efforts had succeeded.

Deomaer left the hall as well. He wandered around the village enjoying the festivities and the great feast provided by his king. The jeweler also took advantage of the many merchants who seemed to have appeared out of nowhere. Thinking ahead to the winter months, he bought himself a new fur-lined robe. The pouch of gold coins which had been given him by Folcwalda and which now hung at his side gave him a certain power he had never before experienced. It also made him the focus of attention of any merchants who happened to discover his new wealth. Though this was at first a boon, it soon became a nuisance. Before long, Deomaer found himself seeking less visible places from which to enjoy the celebration and avoid the merchants. It was only then that he began to notice the frequent disruptions around the village. Princes and their thanes, full of mead, would bump into their counterparts from other tribes and kingdoms, and tempers would flash as if the small collision of two bodies was enough to begin a war—and perhaps it was; Deomaer did not know. At other times seamen would come to blows arguing over the purchase of a piece of cloth or the last pair of leather sandals.

But each and every time there was an outbreak of tempers, just as the situation was about to veer out of control, Ulestan would appear out of nowhere and the disruption would cease as quickly as it had erupted. Or if it wasn’t Ulestan, it was Aelfer or Beow, both of whom the jeweler frequently saw conferring with the elder thane. And as Deomaer watched more closely, he saw something else as well—something which disturbed him greatly. Each time there was a particularly hostile or violent incident, there would be Hunlaf, Oslaf or Guthlaf quietly slipping away from the scene like dogs caught stealing meat. Deomaer wondered if Ulestan saw them too. But he said nothing, for it was not the place of a jeweler to involve himself in the making of treaties or the governing of people. Nonetheless, he shuddered to think what the days would have been like had not Ulestan been at hand and had he not had the wisdom to require all of the arriving bands to leave their weapons in their ships or with their horses in camps outside the village. But Ulestan was there, and the situation never did get out of hand, and Deomaer was able to sleep in peace those nights—or at least in as much peace as could be expected in the midst of such a big celebration in such a small village.

When Finn and Hildeburh emerged sheepishly from their hut near midday on the third day of feasting, Hwitstan was in shambles. Drunk warriors lay scattered at odd angles all across the village; wine and mead cups lay broken and spilled across the grounds; there were more than a few bruised and bloody warriors—victims of overenthusiasm in some of the rougher sporting events; and on the south side of the village ashes still smouldered from a fire which had consumed one hut in the middle of the second night. Surprisingly enough, however, there had not been any fatalities, and there were still enough sober villagers and warriors, both Frisian and alien, to raise a loud cheer for the new couple as they emerged.

“Long live Finn,” the Frisians shouted. “Long live Hildeburh,” echoed the Danes.

“Long live Finn and Hildeburh! Long live Finn and Hildeburh!” everybody joined in.

All arms were raised in salute as the two walked through the clearing and entered the great hall. Hoc and Folcwalda sat watching as if they had been expecting them.

“You return so soon?” Folcwalda asked in jest.

Both Finn and Hildeburh blushed. “The feasting is over,” Finn replied.

“You look well, my daughter,” Hoc said with a smile.

“I am well, Father. More well than I have ever been.”

“Would that I could say the same about all my men,” Folcwalda laughed.

“And I,” Hoc said. “This could be the longest sea voyage any of them have ever taken. I fear the ground is already swaying beneath them.”

“Perhaps you should remain with us for another week,” Folcwalda suggested. Hildeburh gazed at her father and asked the same question with her eyes.

“Another day perhaps.” Hoc smiled back at his daughter. “But not another week. I’m afraid that the new blood bond between our kingdoms might quickly be broken if our men are together much longer.”

“Is that a prophecy?” Hnaef laughed. With his thane Hengest he had stepped up behind his sister and now kissed her on the cheek.

Folcwalda glared. For the first time in three days the smile dropped from his expression. Hnaef didn’t notice. He kept smiling at his sister and new brother.

“Not as long as we rule our people,” Finn replied, returning his smile and extending his arm at the same time.

They grasped each other firmly by the wrists. “Not as long as we rule our people,” Hnaef echoed.

“Then let us share the mead cup and drink to peace. I have grown thirsty, and I’m afraid I’ve missed the best of the celebration.”

“No,” Hnaef laughed. “We’ve missed the best of the celebration. But we did the best we could. There might not be any mead left.”

“No mead? For the prince and his bride?”

“You underestimate your father,” Hoc said. “If I know him at all, the best of the mead still remains. Am I right?” the Dane asked, turning to the Frisian.

“You know me too well, my friend.” Folcwalda smiled. He raised his hand and gestured to a servant, who returned a moment later with a companion. They were carrying six full cups. A small amount of remaining mead was quickly passed around the hall, and some to the village as well.

The two kings rose and stood facing the two princes and the bride.

“We drink to peace between our people,” Folcwalda said.

“We drink to the happiness of the daughter of the Danes,” Hoc added.

“We drink to the bond of blood,” Finn said. Whether he was referring to the bond between himself and Hildeburh or between the Frisians and the Danes, nobody knew and nobody asked.

“We drink to many trips across the sea,” Hnaef finished.

“In both directions,” Hengest added.

Tears came to Hildeburh’s eyes, but she said nothing. Six cups were lifted and drained. Throughout the hall and in the village every hand which held a cup, save for three, was lifted in salute, and every cup which still held mead, save for three, was drained. Only Guthlaf, Oslaf and Hunlaf refrained from drinking, though each held a full cup. Deomaer alone noticed the three cups which tipped slightly to pour a few drops onto the Frisian soil.

•

Summer’s Day celebration was over.

In the end, King Hoc remained more than one day. In fact, he remained another ten as his ships were repaired and his stores resupplied. The work probably could have been done in two or three days, but the king was intent on conversations with Folcwalda. Most of these talks concerned the Merovingians and their king, Chlotar the Younger—or Chlotar Kinslayer as he was called by Folcwalda. But they also spoke of trade rights, customs, and harboring rights for Danish ships. Many agreements were sealed with drink. During that time Finn also had to deal with Réadban as he had promised. But when the Danes had arrived, Réadban had lost heart. He knew his plan had failed, and he was all too eager to receive Finn’s mercy when it was offered. He swore fealty to Folcwalda and Finn and promised tribute to the high kingship.

When Hoc finally left, many more tears were shed—as many by the departing king and prince as by the Danish princess who was left behind. Finn and Hildeburh remained atop the tower long after the Danish ships were out of sight, and then, shortly after the sun disappeared, they slowly walked back to Hwitstan, hand in hand, and entered their new home.